<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A description of the Church of Christ, with her peculiar priuiledges, and also of her commons, and entercommoners With some oppositions and answers of defence, for the maintenance of the truth which shee professeth: against certaine Anabaptisticall and erronious opinions, verie hurtfull and dangerous to weake Christians. Maintained and practised by one Master Iohn Smith, sometimes a preacher in Lincolneshire, and a companie of English people with him now at Amsterdam in Holland. Whome he hath there with himselfe rebaptised. By I.H.</title>
            <author>Etherington, John, fl. 1641-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118987</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854194</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854194</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02435)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1069:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A description of the Church of Christ, with her peculiar priuiledges, and also of her commons, and entercommoners With some oppositions and answers of defence, for the maintenance of the truth which shee professeth: against certaine Anabaptisticall and erronious opinions, verie hurtfull and dangerous to weake Christians. Maintained and practised by one Master Iohn Smith, sometimes a preacher in Lincolneshire, and a companie of English people with him now at Amsterdam in Holland. Whome he hath there with himselfe rebaptised. By I.H.</title>
                  <author>Etherington, John, fl. 1641-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 119, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Stansby] for Nathaniel Fosbrooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Etherington on G2 recto of STC 6607.5--STC.</note>
                  <note>Answers STC 22875: Smyth, John.  The character of the beast.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: To the new sect of rebaptised separatists.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Smyth, John, d. 1612. --  Character of the beast.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Netherlands --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DESCRIPTION OF THE CHVRCH OF Chriſt, with her peculiar Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and alſo of her Commons, and Entercommoners.</p>
            <p>WITH SOME OPPOSITIONS AND ANSWERS OF DEFENCE, For the maintenance of the Truth which <hi>ſhee profeſſeth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AGAINST CERTAINE ANABAPTIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICALL AND ERRONIOVS OPINIONS, Verie hurtfull and dangeroous to weake CHRISTIANS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MAINTAINED AND PRACTISED</hi> By one Maſter IOHN SMITH, ſometimes a Preacher in <hi>Lincolneſhire, and a Companie of Engliſh people</hi> with him now at Amſterdam in <hi>HOLLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whome he hath there with himſelfe Rebaptiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> I. H.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL. 22.13.14.15. VER.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ J am Alpha, and Omega (ſaith the Lord) The firſt and the laſt.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed are they that doe his Commandements, that their right may be in the free of life, and may enter in thorough the Gates into the Citie. For without ſhall be Dogs, and Enchanters, and VVhoremongers, and Murderers, and Idolaters, and whoſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ueth or maketh lies.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Fosbrooke</hi> 1610</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:2"/>
            <head>¶ The principall oppoſitions <hi>are theſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1 THat the Baptiſme of Children is the marke of the Beaſt.</item>
               <item>2 That euery member of a true viſible Church muſt be baptiſed againe.</item>
               <item>3 That none ought to be Baptiſed before hee bee Regenerate.</item>
               <item>4 That the members of their Church are all ſo, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate and baptiſed, and is the heauenly Ieruſalem.</item>
               <item>5 That ſome of theſe may fall away and periſh.</item>
               <item>6 That there is no true Church to be ſeene in the world, but themſelues at this day.</item>
            </list>
            <p>With diuers other falſe Doctrines which are grounded vpon theſe principles.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CITIZENS OF THE HEAVENLY <hi>IERVSALEM.</hi> INCREASE OF TRVETH And heauenly Wiſedome be multiplied <hi>vpon you, with Peace and proſperitie in theſe latter dayes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>And to all her well affected Friends, that deſire to <hi>ſee her Beautie, and to dwell within her</hi> Gates, happie ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Friend of yours ſweete Citizens, vnworthy to take part with you in your riche peculiar things, makes bolde to preſent vnto your cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, treaſures which I haue found. And alſo moſt earneſtly intreates you to aſsiſt me againſt your many enemies, who lay claime to your Citie and all your priuiledges. Pray with me vnto the Lord your God, that his truth may take
<pb facs="tcp:19603:3"/>place in the hearts of men, and bee regarded, and that all the hatefull enemies therof, and their lies may be brought to confuſion. Theſe things I entreat at your hands, making no doubt of your diligence herein. Goe but vp to the top of mount Sion, and you ſhall ſee your enemies round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you with their ſhields in their hands and their ſwords drawne: but be of good courage, feare nothing, your God will deliuer them into your hands, and their weapons ſhall you conſume like ſtraw with the fire of his word, and the Citie ſhall be yours as it is, and it ſhall not he taken from you, nor the treaſures thereof out of your poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion. The daies are come wherin truth ſhall preuaile, And now deere friends to let you vnderſtand my cauſe of writing to the aforenamed Maſter <hi>Iohn Smith</hi> and his company. It fell out of late that I being in company with ſome of them, had ſome conference with them, wherein they ſeemed very well affected to the things that I ſpake vnto them. One of them anſwering me in theſe words, I could willingly let all theſe things which you haue ſaid, goe downe into me, but onely the going to the aſſemblies, another of them anſwered him inſtantly, you heard what he ſayd for that: And ſo they requeſted me that I would ſet the things downe in writing, which had beene ſaid, and they would either anſwere or ſubſcribe vnto it, which thing I thought good to performe.</p>
            <p>And beloued friends, though I be the leaſt worthy of you all to plead your cauſe, yet being mooued at their requeſt, I haue made bold, and alſo ſeeing afterwards ſome writings of theirs publiſhed in Print, I was emboldened the more, perceiuing therein their deſperate reſolution, proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming open war, challenging al, and therin the city of God: I was encouraged, ſeing it was his cauſe, perſwaded he wold
<pb facs="tcp:19603:3"/>be my protector in the defence of his owne Citie, I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tooke his word and promiſe for my ſhield, with this confidence that he would not leaue me till they were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, other weapons I haue none except the ſword of the ſpirit, The ſkill of the learned diſputers of this world looke not for, that is not my profeſsion. Truth I hope yee ſhall find, but veſted in a very low and ſimple Coate, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod I did forget, matter onely was in my mind, the enemy came ſo faſt vpon me that skill was laide aſide. Truth I hope hath kept me company, though I could not garniſh it with Rhetoricall ornaments. And therefore moſt noble and courteous Citizens, I haue made choice of you before all other to Dedicate this meaſure of truth vnto, becauſe I knew, although you be the nobleſt Citizens in the world, yet are ye the pooreſt in ſpirit, your hearts can ſtoope, and your eyes can looke below, you are come downe from the hilles of pride, to the vallies of teares, yet can goe vp to the top of mount Sion; you looke not after the glory of this world, nor the wiſedome thereof, It is fooliſhnes in your thoughts, which are ſeaſoned with heauenly wiſdome, if truth come you embrace it, you looke not vpon the coate of him that brings it, ſo that you iuſtifie I am pleaſed, what others ſay and iudge, (for my part) I paſſe not, but for their parts, I wiſh them to be aduiſed, and to giue eare to the voyce of the Spirit, and the Bride, which crieth, come whoſoeuer is a thirſt, and whoſoeuer will, and take of the water of life freely.</p>
            <p>And to the end your Mother, deere Children of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, might a little refreſh the ſpirits of her well affected friends, that haue beene ſo long time wearied with the Iarres and contentions that haue beene about her viſible ſtate: I thought good to publiſh this ſhort deſcription of
<pb facs="tcp:19603:4"/>her vnto the open veiwe, that they might ſee her fruits what they be, her light, her priuiledges, and her markes, whereby ſhee may bee ſeene and knowne from the fleſhly boaſters of theſe diſtaſtfull times, who hauing beene ſo long accuſtomed to earthen buildings, cannot diſcerne nor taſt that which commeth from aboue, and although not onely the generall, but ſpecially the reformiſts, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, will not onely diſtaſt like wayward children but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſpurne againſt, yet will I not be diſcouraged, for there is a little remnant that thirſteth for reliefe, ſo they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, I paſſe not for the reſt, for I know true wiſedome which is alwaies from aboue, hath beene, is, and ſhall be for euer iuſtified of her Children, and they ſhall ſee Ieruſalem to their great ioy, whereas the other groping in the dark, ſhall neuer behold that holy Citie, nor pertake of her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges for euer. And although ſhe hath cried oft, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered her voice full many a time, and few or none regard what ſhee ſaieth, yet can ſhee not holde her peace, but ſhee muſt pleade her Childrens cauſe, againſt thoſe that lay claime to their right and inheritance, challengeng them the field, and ſetting vp a flagge of defiance againſt the Citie of truth and the God of Iſraell. Behold here comes one the leaſt of ten thouſand, that doth accept the challenge ſeeing others doe hold their peace, and although hee know not how to beare armes in the field as the manner is, yet he promiſeth in the name of the God of Iacob, with a ſling and a ſtone, to bring their champion on his knees, for all his ſtout words, that his army who truſted in him, may be glad to take their flight, and you enioy your Citie in peace, And thus moſt noble Citizens farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull friend till death. <hi>I. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:4"/>
            <head>To M. IOHN SMITH, and to the Companie with <hi>him at Amſterdam in Holland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>H Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> I would for your owne ſake you had not written with ſuch affirmation, Many things which you haue alſo made ſo publike, the which you can neuer call home againe: although you your ſelfe doe finde them falſe, whereby alſo you haue made your ſelfe more vnable and vnwilling to reuoke them, though they be proued ſo. Much better therfore had it bene for you to haue left that Paper vnſtained by your hand, that ſhould paint forth an vntruth, and neuer haue ſet Pen to write, but to the vnchangeable truth of God, of which you neuer neede repent, and whereof the Church of Chriſt is the piller, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering alſo how great a danger euery one doth fall into, that is found to adde or diminiſh from or to the intent and purpoſe of the word of God.</p>
            <p>I would therefore you had beene better aduiſed before you had publiſhed your bookes. You thought your ſelfe as fully ſatisfied when you were of another minde. You know, or at the leſt, there be that know them that haue three, foure, nay, fiue times changed their Religion, that thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as fully ſatisfied euery time as you thnike your ſelfe now: what they are now (ſome of them) I wil not ſay. And if euery man ſhould publiſh bookes ſo often as they change their mind, how many Religions then ſhould ſpring from one man, and he perhaps be author of ſo many ſects, what heapes of bookes are there at this day of ſeuerall opinions? Make therfore no more matter for the fire, there is ſtraw and ſtubble enough already. Speake truth, for the day of burning is at hand. And whatſoeuer you do, looke to the maine, leaue not the foundation as ſome haue done: Hold faſt the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings leaſt you neuer come to the endes. And I pray God deliuer you from the Curſe of <hi>Sinai</hi> and her ſonnes, <hi>Hagars</hi> children. And bring you all vnto the bleſſings of mount Sion and into the reſt and freedome of her children, euen <hi>Saraes</hi> ſonnes and daughters.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your friend. <hi>I. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:5"/>
            <head>¶The Contents of that which followeth.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> A Deſcription of the heauenly Ieruſalem with her priuiledges, and of her ſtability and of her Commons and intercommoners.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> A veiw or ſearch of Maſter <hi>Smiths</hi> Church with a diſcouery of the vnſoundneſse and Ruinouſnes thereof.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> An examination of a principall anſwere of his, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon many of his other reaſons doe depend againſt the Baptiſme of Children, and the confutation thereof: with ſufficient reaſons and proofe for the lawfulnes of Baptizing them, and that the Baptizing of Children cannot be the marke of the Beaſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Of the Commonalty and Commons of Chriſtians in generall, and wherein ſpecially they are to be diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and how the Commoners ought to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues toward the little ſpeciall ones, and how the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall do, and ought to walke towards the Commoners.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Of Chriſtian libertie, and of the lawfulnes of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Magiſtrates, and how all ſubiects are bound to obey.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Of Faith and Repentance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> A Reprehenſion of Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> for his bold Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> An exhortation to him and his company.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> A ſhort deſcription of the contentions of theſe times.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Of Sions Reſtauration, the fall of her greateſt enemy, and of her euerlaſting glory.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:5"/>
            <head>To Maſter IOHN SMITH, and to the Companie with him at Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam in Holland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd leaſt I runne into your fault, and fall into the ſame daunger with you, as of my ſelfe I haue no ſtrength to ſtand more then you: By the grace and aſſiſtance of my God, I will take heede, and though I haue not the skill of the learned Diſputers of this world, yet I hope the Spirit of Trueth will ſo direct me, that I ſhall rather ſay, I know not, then ſet downe and affirme that for trueth, which ſhall be found a lie. This therefore I ſay and write, not reſpecting what you haue ſaid, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding your many Arguments to the contrarie.</p>
            <p>That the Church which the Lord doth build, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of liuing ſtones:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter</hi> 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18.</note> And the gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt that Church, or any one of the ſtones thereof,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20.6.</note> but it ſhall ſtand and preuaile againſt Hell, and the ſnares of the ſecond death, ſo that not one ſhall periſh that is of this holy Temple.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19603:6"/>
            <p> For this Church of Chriſt and euery ſtone there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 7.</note> is framed and faſhioned from aboue, he himſelfe is the foundation and chiefe corner ſtone. And all the ſtones of this building are his brethren, reborne and made a new, not in ſhew, but in very trueth, not for a time, but for euer not, one of them ſhall euer fall off.</p>
            <p>They are all of them euerlaſting, as is their foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation whereon they reſt, and whoſe ſtrength doeth ſtay them vp.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.19.</note> Great priuiledges hath this Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other, for to it hee hath giuen the keyes of the Kingdome of heauen, to open and ſhut, to binde and looſe: And where two or three of this vniuerſall Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.18, 20.</note> conſiſting of ſtones of life, are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in his Name, hee hath promiſed and will not faile to be in the midſt of them, <hi>And whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they binde in earth, is bound in heauen, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they looſe on earth is looſed in heauen:</hi> And where two of them ſhall agree in earth vpon any thing, whatſoeuer yee ſhall, deſire it ſhall bee giuen you (ſaith he) of my Father which is in heauen.</p>
            <p>This Church is one,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.5, 6.</note> the Faith is one, the Baptiſme is alſo one and the ſame in euery ſtone thereof, not on the skinne, but in the heart.</p>
            <p>Their Rocke is Chriſt, that their one Lord, he is the Prince of their Faith and Hope, and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is their one God and Father alone, who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, and through all, and in them all, praiſed for euer.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26.</note> And this is Ieruſalem from aboue, which (Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) is the mother of vs all, and is free.</p>
            <p>And this and all of them are thoſe little ones,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19603:6"/>whom (the Lord ſaid) whoſoeuer ſhall offend: <hi>It were better that a Milſtone were hanged about his necke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>and that he were drowned in the depth of the Sea,</hi> ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in his ſight are they all, <hi>And whoſoeuer ſhall giue but a cup of cold water, to any one of the leſt of theſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke</hi> 9.41.</note> 
               <hi>in my Name</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>ſhall not leeſe his reward, but ſhall haue eternall life,</hi> As it is written; <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world: For I was an hungrie, and you gaue me meate, I was a thirſt and you gaue me drinke, &amp;c. Yee did it to theſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if but to the leaſt of theſe my brethren, yee did it to me;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34, 35, 36.</note> And againe, <hi>Whoſoeuer receiueth one of the leaſt of theſe little ones in my Name</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>receiueth me, and with me him that ſent me.</hi> O happie man therefore, that can perceiue and doe theſe things: But hee that deſpiſeth you, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me, and him that ſent me. And this is it which <hi>Iohn</hi> meaneth. He that ſaith he is in that light,<note place="margin">1. <hi>John</hi> 2.9.</note> and hateth his brother is in darkenes vntill this time: But he which loueth his brother abideth in that light, and there is none occaſion of euill in him. And againe, Hereby we know that we are tranſlated from death to life, becauſe we loue the brethren,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16.</note> meaning the Lords brethren, the little Sheepe, to whom he will ſay, Come yee bleſſed inherit the Kingdome for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: Theſe loue their enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.44.</note> If they hunger they feede them, if they thirſt they giue them drinke, if they curſe they bleſſe, if they perſecute, they pray and weepe for them.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the light of the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.14, 15.</note> the Candle on a Candleſticke, the Citie ſet vpon a Hill, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19603:7"/>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpake when he ſaid, Glorious things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.3.</note> thou Citie of God, and this if one will, he may viſibly ſee, for a Citie ſet vpon a hil cannot bee inuiſible.</p>
            <p>And to this alone is power giuen to binde and looſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.23.</note> to remit and to retaine ſinnes, euen to theſe I meane are theſe Keyes giuen, whom God approueth and will approue for euer: Indeede many are called, but theſe are they that are choſen, theſe loue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and thereby doe they know each other to bee borne of God, and to be loued of God, and that they doe loue God, I ſay, for that they loue thoſe that are borne of God:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.5.</note> As it is written, <hi>Hereby we know that yee are in him.</hi> And this is the kingdome which the Lord ſaith;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>No man can ſee but he that is borne againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is that houſe of <hi>Leui,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 29. <hi>Hebrew.</hi> 12.23.</note> that royall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſpoken of, the peculiar people, the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt borne, who are all written in heauen. The choſen generation, and people ſet at libertie: If you will receiue it;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.4 <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.12.</note> theſe are they that haue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, theſe are all the Prieſts of God, and ſerue in his Temple for euer: Theſe he hath made pillars in his houſe, and ſhall goe no more out: theſe are bleſſed, and holy, and haue al their parts in the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and ſhall not be hurt in the ſecond death. Theſe are they that are riſen with Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2.11.</note> and ſeeke thoſe things which are aboue, who are dead to ſinne and crucified to this world, theſe are they that haue ouercome the world, and haue receiued the white ſtone, and the new name of the Lord. And this is the little flocke to whom he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.32.</note> Be of good cheere, for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19603:7"/>it is your fathers pleaſure to giue you a kingdome. And this alone is that Citie of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.11.</note> which onely is named the new Ieruſalem, and theſe are the Citizens, and of theſe the ſcripture meanes, which ſaith, Where two or three be gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them, And behold I am with you (ſaith he) vnto the end of the world.</p>
            <p>But perhaps you will ſay, if this bee the Church of Chriſt, which you haue here deſcribed; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> to whome the Keyes of the Kingdome of heauen, and all thoſe titles and priuiledges doe onely belong: then was there neuer ſuch a Church in the world, in one fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip congregated and conſtituted by baptiſme, pertaking together in the Lords ſupper, and all other exerciſes of Religion, conſiſting onely of ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable ſtones as you ſpeake of: For with the Lord himſelfe, and with his eleuen Apoſtles one was, who did prooue a diuell, And many alſo were with Chriſt before and were Baptiſed, which fell away, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with his Apoſtles alſo which fell away and were offended.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, but what ſaith it, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.19.</note> If they had bin of vs, they would haue continued with vs: but of that Church they neuer were, that hath the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, and vnto whom thoſe excellent titles and treaſures of God doth belong: for although they did partake with them in receiuing the word, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the truth thereof, and of the elementiſh Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and the ſignes of the Lords bodie and blood, and all other ſuch like common things: yet were they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer baptiſed in heart, returned and became as little
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19603:8"/>children; neither yet did euer eat his fleſh, and drinke his blood,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat:</hi> 18.3.</note> truly and indeed by faith: for want wherof, they could neuer enter into the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: nor yet had euer life in them, as it is written. And therefore of that Church and kingdome they neuer were,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.53.</note> nor yet did euer partake with them in their peculiar things: nor neuer came into their courts of reſt, nor Citie of peace. But to the retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned little ones, doe all thoſe great things belong; thoſe excellent priuiledges, euen to them that eate his fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.54.</note> and drinke his blood: who haue all of them eternall life abiding in them, whom the Lord Ieſus will raiſe vp at the laſt day, as he himſelfe ſaith.</p>
            <p>But how then did that Church iudge of them, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> (you will ſay) while they were with them? did they not beleeue that they were returned, and did they not accompt of them, as they did of thoſe that were returned and borne againe: that had eaten Chriſts fleſh, and drunke his blood vnto eternall life: ſeeing they were baptiſed with them, and did eate the ſame bread, and drinke the ſame wine with them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, did they not iuſtifie them, and approue of them as of the reſt?</p>
            <p>That Church did neuer ſo approue of them, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> they were neuer ſo blind and deſperatly bold, as your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Smith,</hi> to iuſtifie and approoue of thoſe whom God doth condemne: they are not ſo raſh as you, and your Church, to affirme they know not what: They are better aduiſed, and better taught then ſo: That Church &amp; kingdome which we ſpeake of, was neuer ſo deceiued in her enterco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moners, to account
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19603:8"/>and approue them as borne againe: becauſe they did partake with her children in all theſe common things: But ſhe and her children iudged alwayes the truth of them, and neuer were deceiued concerning them.</p>
            <p>They receiued the word with ioy and gladneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. <hi>Luke</hi> 9 62.</note> They tooke the Plough by the hand indeed, The foule ſpirit was gone, the Sowe was waſht, the blade ſprung vp: Theſe things the Church did ſee, and know was true in them; and ſo farre it did approoue of them, &amp; did yeeld vnto them the common things, and were of one accord therein together. The Church &amp; ſtones of life looked for fruit from them, but fruit they neuer ſaw: They hoped the beſt, till they ſaw the worſt: They knew not the tree, but by the fruit, and that not till it had brought forth, either good or bad. But by their fruit they do know them as it is written, Doe men gather Grapes of Thornes, or Figges of Thiſtles? can a good tree bring foorth bad fruit, or a bad tree good fruit? no not poſſible. A good tree cannot bring foorth euill fruit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16.17.18.19.20.</note> neither can a bad tree bring foorth good fruit: euery tree that bringeth not foorth good fruit, is hewen downe and caſt into the fire. The Scripture doth neuer any where teach or ſpeake like your Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> That euill trees may be knowen to be good trees, by bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of good fruit, and yet be cut downe and caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell fire, for bearing of euill fruit: for you ſay, that a tree which ſhall be hewen downe, one that may fall away, doth bring forth as good fruit, as the good tree, or good ground doth; and that there can no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19603:9"/>difference be diſcerned by their fruits between them, contrary to the Scripture which ſaith to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the kingdome.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.33.</note> Yee ſhall know them by their fruits, Meaning the good trees by the good fruit which they bring foorth, from the trees that bring not foorth good fruit, and from the euill trees which bring foorth euill fruite. And as they knowe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, the good tree by his good fruit, and the euill tree by his euill fruit: ſo they doe alſo know that thoſe trees which growe in the Lords field,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.6.7.8.</note> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as branches in the vine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.2.</note> and bring not foorth good fruit are accurſed like the figge tree,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10.</note> &amp; muſt be hewen downe with the euill trees, and caſt into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire.</p>
            <p>But perhaps you will ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> theſe trees cannot be ſo diſtinguiſh't and knowne till the end, for the Lord ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.13.</note> He that endureth to the end, ſhall be ſaued. And the righteous man may fall from his righteouſneſſe (as teſtifieth the Prophet) and die.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 18.24.26.27.</note> And the vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man turne from his vnrighteouſneſſe and liue. So that there can be no ſuch certainty as you ſpeake of, vntill the end.</p>
            <p>Heere I would firſt know of you, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> what ende you thinke the Lord doth meane, whether the end of the world, or the end of their life in the fleſh? If you mean the end of the world, then <hi>Moſes, Elias,</hi> the Prophets, and Apoſtles might yet periſh, for to that ende they are not yet come: But they are and ſhall bee ſaued, therefore that end it cannot be: what then? the ende of their life in the fleſh? that end is it which you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, I dare ſay, Then indeed there is no certainty, in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19603:9"/>this world to be had, till the houre of death: then is the Doctrine of your fellowes, the Dutch Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts true, who affirme that the moſt righteous man, luſtified and borne againe from aboue, may fal away and periſh at any time, euen till his laſt howre: then ſhould mans ſaluation depend vpon his laſt gaſpe. Then no man can reioyce, that his name is written in the Booke life, till he be dead: or elſe they may haue their names blotted out againe, after they be written therein, as indeede they doe affirme: But man may be certainely aſſured of reconciliation with God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.38.30.</note> and that his name is written in the booke of life and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led there, by an indelible couenant, before the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or houre, or day of his death, therefore that end it cannot be.</p>
            <p>But ſtay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> may not the righteous man fall from his righteouſnes then?</p>
            <p>Such righteous men, as I told you of before, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> may fall from their righteouſneſſe, Euill Trees and euill ground which neuer brought foorth good fruit. As from ſome the foules of the Aire catch away the ſeed that is ſowne in their harts, and they fall away:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.19.20.21.22.</note> ſome by perſecution are offended, &amp; ſome the cares of this world doe choake. And ſo the righteous man doth fall from his righteouſneſſe. The waſhed ſow is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to wallow in the mire againe.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pe.</hi> 20.2.</note> The dogge to his vomit againe. He that tooke the Plough by the hand, hath looked behind him, and is made vnmeete for the kingdome of heauen for, euer. The vncleane ſpirit that was caſt out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.45.</note> is returned with ſeauen worſe then himſelfe, and re-entereth the houſe ſwept: and the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19603:10"/>ende of this man is worſe then his beginning: It had beene better for him, that he had neuerknowne the way of truth, his condition was better before hee tooke the Plough in hand, then it is now in this end of his, wherein he hath giuen it ouer, turned backe &amp; entertained his euill companion againe, with ſeauen more worſe then he.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> But what is then the end, which whoſoeuer endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto, and doth attaine, ſhall be ſaued?</p>
            <p>The end therefore is the fruit, as reaping is the end of Ploughing: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> And as wee looke for fruite after wee haue ſowne our Corne in the earth: So doth the Lord looke for fruit of the ſeede he hath ſowne in vs. Such fruite as whoſoeuer bringeth forth, ſhall neuer be hewen downe and giuen to the burning fire. But is like the tree planted by the riuer ſide,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.3.</note> which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth his fruit in due ſeaſon, whoſe leafe ſhall not fade.</p>
            <p>And this is the plantation of God, and theſe are his trees, and the branches of his owne Vine Chriſt Ieſues: and euery branch that berareth fruit in him hee purgeth like a good husbandman,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.1.2.</note> that it may bring forth more fruit. And if you aske what fruit that is, I tolde you before: yet if you will haue it againe, It is Loue, euen that new commaundement, the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Lord commaundeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48.</note> ſaying. Be ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as your heauenly Father is perfect: It is the firſt reſurrection, which whoſoeuer attaineth, is bleſſed &amp; holy for euer. They that attaine to this end, are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.3.45.6 <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.</note> and bleſſed at their houre of death, and bleſſed at the end of the world, and bleſſed for euermore.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19603:10"/>
            <p> Theſe righteous men neuer fall from their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, their names are neuer raſed out of die booke of life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.14.</note> but vnrighteous men may turne to their righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes. And therfore theſe righteous men, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all, exhorte all, hope all things, endure all things, forbeare and are gentle vnto all,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4.5.6.7.8.</note> And wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te with patience, laboring to ſee it by any means, they will bring forth fruit, euen the fruit of the good tree, The good fruitwhich when they ſee, they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice &amp; imbrace them, knowing thereby that they are borne of God their owne father, as Children of that holy Church Ieruſalem their mother: purged and purchaſed through his eternall Teſtament, in the bloud of that one Lord the Lambe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>John</hi> 3.14.</note> to be an holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation to himſelfe for euer. And here is no loue loſt betweene theſe brethren, ſuch loue betweene them as neuer was betweene earthly brethren.</p>
            <p>As the ſtocke they came of in their new generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth excell in glory, inriches, in power,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.1.</note> in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in bounty, in mercy, and loue: all Fathers and Mothers in nature, be they neuer ſo high in place of this world, euen that they can giue Kingdomes, and thouſand thouſands of Gold and Treaſure, to their Children: and poſſeſſe them of all the pleaſures that the world can afford: and with all the ſignes of loue that nature can expreſſe. I ſay, as the great God of Heauen doth excell the greateſt that euer was on earth: And as his loue is infinite beyond theirs, and his abilitie alſo to performe the ſame: So doe the gifts, the ſignes and ſeales of his loue excell theirs.</p>
            <p>And as his children doe come of a more noble
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19603:11"/>ſtocke then theirs and are more honourablie deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded euery way. So doe they excell in loue ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand degrees, for ehey loue for other and greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. And as loue was the beginning and cauſe of this happineſſe:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.19.</note> euen the loue of the eternall God, as the Scriptures witneſſe: So loue is the end of their conuerſation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.</note> in and through Ieſus Chriſt, yeſterday to day, and the ſame for euer.</p>
            <p>This is that name ſo ſecretly written vpon them, that no man can Reade or know it, but they alone which haue it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.12.</note> and vpon them onely is his Name written: New Ieruſalem; as it is written: Him that ouercommeth, will I make a Pillar in the Temple of my God: And he ſhall goe no more out; And I will write vpon him the name of my God, and the name of the Citie of my God, euen the newe Ieruſalem which commeth downe from heauen from my God, And my new name. And this is the ende, which whoſoeuer endureth vnto, is faithfull to the death, and ſhall receiue the Crowne of life. Many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe and deceiue many,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.11.12.13.</note> and becauſe iniquitie ſhall abound, the loue of many ſhall bee cold; but he that endureth to the end, euen this true and perfect loue, the contrarie to iniquitie, and to loue that is cold, he ſhall be ſaued.</p>
            <p>And this is the Baptiſme of the holy Ghoſt and fire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11.</note> euen the fire of Gods loue, the coals wherof are fiery coales, and a burning flame which much water can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not quench, neither the flouds drowne: But it brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth foorth and returneth ſuch a loue to his God and Father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an.</hi> 8.7.</note> and to his Lord and redeemer, as no man
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19603:11"/>knoweth, but he that hath it. And ſuch a loue to his fathers Children, thoſe little ones, his and his Lords brethren, as they neuer know nor ſhall know who are neuer borne againe.</p>
            <p>Yea, he returneth loue to al men euen to his enemies.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20, 21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.2, 4.</note> If he hunger or thirſt he feedes and giues them drink, and ſo heapes coales of this fire vpon his head. Hee ſpeaketh the truth from his hart, and with his tongue vſeth no deceit. Hee eſteemeth not himſelfe, but is vile in his owne eyes. Hee enuieth not.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4, 5, 6.</note> The Sunne goes not downe vpon his anger: Hee reioyceth not in iniquitie, but alwayes in the trueth, and in doing good to others: Loue ſeeketh not her owne. And are not theſe fruits which may diſtinguiſh betweene the good tree and the bad?</p>
            <p>Theſe fruites thoſe righteous men neuer brought foorth, which fell away.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14.</note> Their blade was neuer like this fruit: Their beginnings were neuer like theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. Thoſe firſt were neuer like theſe laſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.14.</note> which are the firſt, euen the firſt borne; For many are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led but fewe choſen.</p>
            <p>And this is Ieruſalem, that poore little ſweete ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Citie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 11 2.</note> which hath bene troden vnder feete of thoſe heathen Gentile Courtiers, and outſide Chriſtians, not worth the meaſuring, theſe many hundred yeres. And this is the Hill which once ſtood vp aboue the Hils, whoſe light did ſhine from Eaſt to Weſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8.</note> euen to the worlds end. To it the Nations flocke to heare, and ſee the things that were of her ſo famous throgh the world. To whom ſhee cried, ſaying: Come whoſoeuer will, and take of the water of life freely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22.17.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19603:12"/>whereat many reioyced, beleeued and were Baptiſed. Of which ſome were made pet takers of her peculiar things: And were not onely beleeuers of the trueth, and Baptiſed with the Baptiſme which thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed, but were Baptiſed in heart broken and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into a thouſand teares: And beleeued in him who alſo Baptiſed them with the holy Ghoſt and fire. The other hard and vnbaptiſed in heart, refuſing that graceſo freely offered them: Iudging the common Faith and Baptiſme which they had receiued, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſerue their turne: Suppoſing that one Talent ſafely kept, would ſtand them enough inſteede when the day of account ſhould come; deſpiſed the little ones that were borne and Baptiſed from aboue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.29.</note> And thus began the myſterie of iniquitie to worke, and grew vp in time aboue the Hill of God, and like Wolues ſpared not his flocke, tooke poſſeſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede of the outward Court, gathered ſtrength, got a head: And trode downe that liberall free Citie, the true mother and nurſe to the Lords lambes and babes.</p>
            <p>This head of theirs is that great Antichriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 13.1.</note> that beaſt which roſe out of the ſea, with ſeuen heads and ten hornes: who hath reigned now twelue hundreth and three yeeres, and yet ſtill reigneth, and ſhall till ſeuen and fiftie moe be come. And then his dayes his times,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 11.3.</note> moneths and yeeres, ſhall be accompliſht, (euen one thouſand two hundred and ſixtie.) and his Crownes puld from his head, his Citie burnt with fire, and vpon that woman which ſaith: I ſit being a Queene, am no widow, and ſhall ſee no mourning,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19603:12"/>ſhall come ſhame and confuſion, howling and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and vtter deſolation: euen ſhe which now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth her ſelfe by the name of the true mother, and like an harlot challengeth the husband of the true ſpouſe to bee hers.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35.</note> And theſe are the ofspring of <hi>Caine,</hi> the race and line of thoſe Pharaſies, at whoſe hands the Lord ſaid ſhould be required the blood of all the Prophets, from righteous <hi>Abell</hi> to <hi>Zacharias;</hi> yea, theſe are all one houſe with them. And ſo are all the aſſemblies and congregations in the world, be they neuer ſo cleane without, doing the ſame works, being foule within: and doe make one and the ſame generation with them, and with all ſuch heathen in the world, being vncircumciſed in heart like them. To fulfill the word of the Lord which ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 8.24.</note> That in her ſhould be found the blood of all, that euer for righteouſneſſe were ſlaine vpon the earth. Prouing indeed that all that are vncleane in heart, and doe the ſame workes, doe make one generation, be they what they will. Theſe are all the euill ſeed, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the wicked<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of the bond woman, This is <hi>Hagar</hi> and her ſonne which muſt be caſt out, Theſe are the ſerpents ſeed that neuer did loue the ſeed of the woman.</p>
            <p>But you Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> vnderſtand not theſe things ſo, you ſhut out <hi>Hagars</hi> houſe from theſe times, you will haue the Church of another faſhion, you will haue it of your owne building; you like not the frame which the Lord alloweth: you will not haue ſo many ſorts of veſſels in the Lords great houſe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20.</note> as the Scriptures doe ſpeake off, and yet you will haue
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19603:13"/>more in his little ſpirituall houſe then the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. You will not haue veſſels of gold, of ſiluer, of wood and of clay; ſome to honour, ſome to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, in his great houſe, together in commons: And yet you will haue veſſels of diſhonour to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in the peculiar things pertaining onely to his little houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18.</note> and to be of it. But the beſt is, the Lord hath not made you the builder of his houſe, hee meanes to build ſtill as hee hath euer done his little ſpirituall houſe himſelfe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32 <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.27</note> hee will hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the veſſels thereof all of gold and ſiluer, prepared to honour: build you and prepare the other of wood and clay; for although this great houſe be all one in commons, yet it is two in ſpecials: which ſhall be more at large diſtinguiſhed hereafter. But wee will firſt ſee what faſhion your houſe is of.</p>
            <p>You ſay, all that you baptiſe, are firſt borne againe; and being borne againe, and baptiſed, they are all Citizens of the heauenly Ieruſalem, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the firſt borne: the peculiar people, and holy nation, thoſe returned little ones, which the Lord ſpake of. And that none but ſuch ought to be baptiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.14</note> and that whoſoeuer is baptiſed before he is reborne of the ſpirit: that baptiſing is Antichriſtian, and muſt be reuoked He muſt firſt be a new creature, and then rebaptiſed. And yet you ſay ſome of theſe may fall away and periſh. This is your Church you ſay, and ſo it is conſtituted. Indeede, you haue framed it finely, but it will not ſtand.</p>
            <p>The foundation is ſand, and the toppe is ſo light, that the winde will carrie it away to periſh: for ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19603:13"/>you ſay, and it may well be; for an errour in the ground worke doth argue ſlight worke in the raiſing and finiſhing: for he that is careleſſe in laying the foundation of his houſe: will ſurely be very negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in the framing and ending thereof: and if a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workeman ſhould ſearch that houſe, he ſhould doubtleſſe find many vnſound ioints therein.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> But ſome man perhaps will ſay, that Maſter <hi>Smithes</hi> foundation is very ſound and ſure, for hee begins with regeneration, and hee will haue none baptiſed into his Church, till hee be borne of God: and who can lay a more ſure foundation then this?</p>
            <p>Indeed a faire ſhew it makes, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> but we will ſearch it from the toppe to the bottome: for though he that builds a houſe, doth firſt begin with the foundation and bottome thereof; yet he that will pull downe that houſe, had neede firſt begin at the top. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee will ſearch it from the top to the bottome, and by that time I hope wee ſhall ſee whether it bee ſound or no.</p>
            <p>Your concluſion is, that ſome of your Church may fall away, and ſhall periſh; and yet you ſay, they are all of them thoſe little ones whom our Sauiour ſpeaketh of: this is euen as contrary as ſaluation and damnation: for the ſame Lord ſaith. It is not the will of your heauenly Father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.14.</note> that one of theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones ſhould periſh, but your will is, they ſhall.</p>
            <p>The Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23.</note> that the Congregation of the firſt borne, are written in heauen: but you ſay ſome of them are written in hell. Chriſt ſaith, the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt his Church,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19603:14"/>and many other moſt ſure promiſes, that the ſecond death ſhall take no hold of any one of the leaſt ſtones thereof;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20.6</note> but you dare boldly affirme the contrarie. And yet you will baptiſe none, but ſuch as are borne a new, you ſay: and that none ought to bee baptiſed, but ſuch a litle one; which is the beginning &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of your building. And how contrary are theſe things? How weake and rotten is your worke, from the top to the bottome? For whereas you ſay, that none ought to bee baptized, but they muſt be firſt borne againe, it is vtterly falſe: for the Scripture ſaith that Ieſus made &amp; baptiſed moe Diſciples then <hi>Iohn.</hi> And it ſaith alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.1. <hi>John.</hi> 6.53.60.</note> that when the Lord told them, that except they did eate his fleſh, and drinke his blood, they had no life in them (which is the chiefe and principall point of regeneration) they anſwered, It was a hard ſaying, who could indure it? which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth euidently they were neuer borne againe, and yet baptiſed: for euery Diſciple was baptiſed. And they were Diſciples, the text faith: and whatſoeuer he were that did ſubiect himſelfe to learne, and came into the fellowſhip, was one of the diſciples, though he were not one of the new borne babes. Theſe things are as cleere as the light throughout the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: but you being ignorant of the Scriptures through your wiſdome, would delude vs with doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and double ſpeeches, as you do ſome innocent, (as I hope) and vpright ſoules, that depend vpon your wiſedome and skill, whoſe conſciences (I perſwade my ſelfe) doe tell them, al is not well.</p>
            <p>You ſtriue ſo much to make your Church differ
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19603:14"/>from the Church of the Iewes: becauſe you miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, would haue the whole eſtate of the Iewes Church containe the bond woman and her ſonne, and the whole ſtateof the Gentiles Church to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the free woman and her ſonne: ſo that you will haue your Church not onely to differ from the Iewes Church, but from the very word and practiſe of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and from the Church that then was.</p>
            <p>You will not haue a ſonne of the free woman in the Iewes Church, nor the ſonne of a bond woman in the Gentiles Church: but all muſt ſhew forth the fruits of regeneration that ought to be baptiſed, and ſo conſequently being all reborne and baptiſed, muſt needs bee the children of the free woman. What a Laborinth haue you brought your ſelfe &amp; your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany into? You will haue all your Church to be the ſpirituall ſeed of <hi>Abraham:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26.</note> and yet that ſome of them may, and ſhall prooue caſt-awayes, contrary to the Scriptures which ſaith, All Iſrael ſhall be ſaued: mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed, Iewes or Gentiles.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible that ye can be ignorant, how in the Churches of the Apoſtles times, there were many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill workers euidently knowen, vnreturned, earthly minded; of whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Many wake,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17.18.19</note> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue told you often, &amp; now tel you weeping, &amp;c. Is not this manifeſtly to be ſeene throughout all the new Teſtament?</p>
            <p>Did the Lord himſelfe who knewe all thinges, entertaine Diſciples,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.64.</note> baptiſing them whom hee knew did not beleeue in him, nor yet were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19603:15"/>yea one, whom hee knewe ſhould betray him.</p>
            <p>The Lord, I ſay, who could haue made his choiſe, and haue taken the beſt, and left the worſt at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: If he had beene ſo diſpoſed, or had intended to make the outer Court of his temple, as pure as the temple it ſelfe, whereunto none doth come to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but onely his royall Prieſthood. Did the Lord, (I ſay ſtill) who knew all things, doe thus to teach vs in theſe caſes, what to doe to the worlds end? And dare you which know nothing in compariſon, take vpon you to teach him, and to contradict his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe? Did hee entertaine all that came to him into his outward Court, yeelding vnto them all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things thereof? And dare you ſo boldly to change his ordinance, reiecting ſuch as then hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained: If hee had intended, that none ſhould be baptized, but ſuch as brought forth the fruites of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, hee would not haue then baptized, nor haue ſuffered any to be baptized, that were not firſt regenerate, ſeeing that he knew them one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he would haue giuen vs example both by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his Apoſtles: and would not haue baptized any one,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.39.</note> but <hi>Abrahams</hi> true ſpirituall ſeede, who ſhould firſt haue wrought the works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of whom not one ſonne of perdition ſhould euer haue beene found. This would the Lord haue done, I ſay, if his will and truth had ſo been in this outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his Kingdome, he would haue performed it perſectly. Seeing hee could doe in this caſe what he would, he would not haue beene found vnfaithfull
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19603:15"/>in his houſe, (as it is plaine hee was, if that doctrine of yours be true.) All agree that the ſinne of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is greater then the ſinne of ignorance. Did Chriſt know his Fathers will was, that none ſhould be baptized but <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed, and would he baptize thoſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.60.</note> that knew not what it was to eate his fleſh and drinke his bloud, which all <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed did both eate and drinke of, and therefore muſt needes know what it is? would he haue entertained <hi>Iudas,</hi> and baptized him, ſeeing he knew from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning that he was the child of perdition, and that he ſhould betray him?</p>
            <p>No, no, Chriſt our Lord would neuer haue done all theſe things, if he had knowne his Fathers will, to haue beene contrary, he would neuer haue ſinned ſo highly againſt his Father with his knowledge (as he did, if that be true which you affirme.)</p>
            <p>But you are the lyar and the ſinner: be it knowne vnto you. It is you that breake the law of God, and violate the word and waies of Chriſt, by your curſed wayes and doctrine. For his will is, that common things ſhould be for the many that are called, but his peculiar things for the few that are choſen: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee compareth the common Court and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, to a Net caſt into the Sea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.47.</note> which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all ſorts of fiſh both good and bad. And his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall kingdome and holy temple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.31. <hi>and</hi> 33.</note> he compareth to a graine of Muſtard ſeed, to Leauen, To a field where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in lieth a treaſure hid of great worth, which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer will enioy, muſt purchaſe it with all hee hath.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.44.45.46.</note> Which Kingdome, the Lord ſaith; Except a man be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19603:16"/>borne againe he ſhall neuer enter into, nor ſee.</p>
            <p>Perceiue you not theſe things M. <hi>Smith?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.3.</note> are they hidden from your eies?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.52.</note> Then are you not the Scribe which the Lord ſpeaketh of, which is taught vnto the kingdome of heauen, compared to a houſholder which bringeth forth of his treaſurie, things both new and olde.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> But peraduenture you will yet obiect, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be ſome caught in the Net, that doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards proue bad, yet they were good when they were firſt caught, and brought forth good fruite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were baptized; and therefore Chriſt gaue Rules to his Church, to the end that when any ſhould offend, if he would not be reformed, after he had beene orderly dealt withall by the Church: that then hee ſhould be caſt out, and ſo cut off from the bodie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> Is it poſſible that a branch of the Vine which brought forth good fruite, ſhould euer bee cutte off from the Vine, for bearing of euill fruit: ſeeing God is the husbandman of his vine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.1.2.</note> and euery branch that bringeth forth good fruite, the ſame he purgeth that it may bring forth more fruit? Did you euer read in all the Scriptures: that a good man one of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſeed, which brought forth good fruit, and did the workes of <hi>Abraham:</hi> that afterwards prooued an euill man? and brought forth euill fruit, and was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cut of for euer from the vine, and from <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall houſe? Hath Chriſt giuen rules to this end, to cut of fruitfull branches, Citizens of the heauenly Ieruſalem? (for ſo ye call them all whom yee Baptiſe)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19603:16"/>His rules are not for you, if you can rule no better then ſo.</p>
            <p>But hee hath giuen them to his Church, you ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> and we know no Church he hath but ours?</p>
            <p>Know ye not indeed? are ye altogether ignorant? What ſay you to Maſter <hi>Francis Iohnſon</hi> and his company at Amſterdam? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> They boſt as much of rules as you. And to all the ſeuerall companies of your fellow Anabaptiſts, who haue beene ſuch auncient profeſſors of your faith? Haue you ſhut them all out of dores to day, and came in your ſelues but yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day? Is this the rule you keepe?</p>
            <p>I pray you tell vs one thing Maſter <hi>Smith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what rule baptiſed you your ſelfe? what worde or example had you for that in all the Scriptures? Doe you affirme the baptiſme of children to be the marke of the Beaſt, becauſe, you ſay, there is no word nor example in all the Scripture, to proue that they may be baptiſed: And yet durſt you preſume without either word or example, to baptiſe your ſelfe? If you go about to proue that lawful which you haue done, by any word, or example in the Scripture, I ſay you cannot ſet one ſtep forward to that purpoſe, but you muſt allow thereby the baptiſme of Children. I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell you did not preuent this obiection: which wil be as hard a bone for you to gnaw vpon, as you thinke the baptiſme of Children is to vs. It was wonder you wold not receiue your baptiſme firſt, from ſome one of the Elders of the Dutch Anabaptiſts; but you will be holyer then all, and ſee how you haue marred all.</p>
            <p>And you Church your ſelues, you ſay, and put
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19603:17"/>a Church vpon your ſelues. What ſtrange doubtfull ſpeech is this? What kind of Church is that you put vpon your ſelues, and Church your ſelues withall? Doe you meane a Church of lime and ſtone, made by mens hands? Such a Church you may Church you withall, and put vppon your ſelues when you will.</p>
            <p>But that is not your meaning, I dare ſay, that is an abhomination in your eyes. Your meane (If I miſtake not) Two or three gathered together  Doe pull Chriſt vnto them, and ſo Church Chriſt, and not themſelues; to ſpeake ſenſiblie. And is this your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning indeede ſir? where read you or euer heard you of the like?</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſaith to as good men as you (none diſprai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) you haue not Choſen me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.16.</note> but I haue choſen you And vpon this Rocke will I (not Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> and his company) build my Church, nor any company in the world elſe, And the gates of Hell ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naile againſt it. And will yee know now to what Church he giueth theſe rules, if ye call them ſo. And I giue vnto it, ſaith hee, the Keyes of the kingdome of Heauen. And where two or three be gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name (I would you knew what this [In my name] doth intend) there am I in the middeſt of them, as if he had ſaid, where two or three of theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle returned ones that beleeue in me, whom my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will is, ſhall be ſaued, doe at any time or in any place gather together, in the ſame faith and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence put in my name, there will I be in the middeſt of them; that is, there will I make my habitation, my Church and my dwelling place.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.7.</note> This is the ſpirituall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19603:17"/>Canaan and land of reſt, and this is the little houſe whoſe veſſells are all of gold and ſiluer.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.8.12.13.</note> But in the groat houſe there are veſſels of gold, ſiluer, wood, and clay, and they are but one in commons together, but two in the ſpeciall peculiar things: Which are not diſtinguiſhed by baptiſme, but by regeneration;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</note> the birth of water and of the holy Ghoſt, and other ſuch like great and peculiar things.</p>
            <p>And tell me are ye all entred into that reſt? Are ye all the free womans Children? Are yee all borne of God?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 29.</note> Is there not one amongſt you that loues not his brother?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19.</note> Is there not one among you that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines Hereſie, which is a thing neceſſary, that thoſe which are approoued might bee knowne? Is there neuer a one weake amongſt you, are yee all ſtrong men in Chriſt Ieſus?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1.7.</note> Is there none of you carnall and yet in your ſinnes, that had need be exhorted to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harden his heart, and to ſtudy to enter into that reſt, leaſt he be depriued of his expectation? Is there not one of all the to amongſt you? Are ye all as one, &amp; one as al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s there neuer a better, nor worſe? are ye al bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed with that one Baptiſme ſpoken of, &amp; pertakers of that firſt reſurrection? Is this your ſaying indeed? Hath the water of Holland waſhed ye all ſo cleane? ils Indeede if all theſe things be ſo, then there is no to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon between the Iewes Church &amp; yours, nor yet betweene the Church of the Apoſtles dayes, and yours; but great difference. Though yet betweene the Church of Chriſt in the Apoſtles dayes, and the Church of Chriſt vnder the law, there was neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch difference as ye pretend. For they had all the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19603:18"/>ſame Goſpell and faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.18. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.17.</note> preached the ſame baptiſme of repentance, and purging of the holy Ghoſt, euen the very ſame way of entring into his reſt; and ſome were made pertakers thereof, and entred thereinto; &amp; had the ſame keies committed vnto them, that are ſtill giuen to Chriſts Church. Although with many of them that did pertake in Commons with them, God was not pleaſed, I meane thoſe that were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in the Sea, and circumciſed in the skin, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their ſacrifices in common with them, as did <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel.</hi> And who might for bid <hi>Cain</hi> to offer or <hi>Iſmael</hi> to be circumciſed, or the hard-hearted Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites their baptiſme in the Sea, or the whole houſe of Iſrael, to come and offer vpon the braſen Altar, that ſtood in the Court of the temple?</p>
            <p>So now likewiſe and in all times, were and ſhall be common things for all, and peculiar things for the peculiar. The leaſt grace is to be cheriſhed: none ought to be diſcouraged;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.22.</note> 
               <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to pray: They that beleeued the Goſpels truth, were baptiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41.</note> and receiued the ſignes of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and bloud alſo.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21.</note> In theſe common things they did pertake with Chriſts holy Prieſthood, his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Church. But you ſay theſe things are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon now. They were common once when trueth tooke place, as the Scriptures by examples proue: I meane, to ſuch as did beleeue the Goſpell, and did not profeſſe the practiſe of iniquity, but profeſſed the Goſpel and the truth thereof; though they were not circumciſed in heart, regenerate and become as little children,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.66.</note> any more then the Diſciples were that fell
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19603:18"/>away from Chriſt: and thoſe who asked, who ſhould be the greateſt, and many other moe which the new Teſtaments examples proue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For tell me, ſhall euery one that is baptiſed in the right forme and manner (for that ye ſtand much on) vpon the skinne, bee ſaued? And euery one that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth the Communion of the Lords body and blood (I meane the ſigne thereof) be ſaued? I thinke you will ſay no: then ſay I, they are common. As on the other ſide, to beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, to put our truſt in God through him, to eate his fleſh and drinke his blood: is eternall life, and is peculiar to his Church alone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.54.</note> in the middeſt of whom he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> But you ſay: we iudge all ſo, that are baptiſed, though God iudge otherwiſe. Doe you ſo indeed, doth God iudge one thing, and iudge you another? doth God ſay one thing, and ſay you another? And doe you know one thing, when God knoweth the contrary: or dare yee affirme that which yee know not? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> I perceiue I muſt ſpeake plainely vnto you, you are ſo dull of hearing.</p>
            <p>Tell me I pray you, did euer Chriſts Apoſtles and true Church affirme any to be borne of God, that prooued otherwiſe? Did they euer iuſtifie whom God condemned, or condemne, whom God iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Indeed the Lord ſaith to the Phariſees, you iudge after the outward appearance:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.24.</note> but iudge righteous iudgement.</p>
            <p>Yee make cleane the outſide, ſaith he, but if you would make cleane the inſide,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.26.</note> the outſide ſhould bee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19603:19"/>cleane alſo.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.42.</note> They were ſtrict in all ſmall common things, but the weightie matters they left vndone: mercy and iudgement they ought to haue looked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,<note place="margin">1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>win.</hi> 11.31. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.7.</note> which proueth men bleſſed, as it is written. If you would iudge your ſelues, you ſhould not be iudged: And bleſſed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercy.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> A man may be borne againe to you, though he be not borne againe to God: for we iudge as farre as we ſee by his fruits. If we iudge him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of baptiſme, he is then borne againe (to me you ſay.)</p>
            <p>I pray you is there one new birth to you, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to God? will ye haue a man borne againe and againe? will ye haue two regenerations, one to you, and another to God: one eſſentiall, another in ſhew?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.3.</note> The Lord ſaith, Except a man be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine (meaning once) of water and the holy Ghoſt, he cannot enter into the Kingdome of God: Not twice, once to you, and once to God. But you iudge as far you ſee (you ſay) but why iudge you farther then you ſee? tell me that. For you ſay without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, that all thoſe whom you haue rebaptiſed, are reborne of repentance and of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaning of the Scriptures. And yet you ſay, that ſome of theſe may fall away and periſh for euer. Is it poſſible that a man may bee borne of God and periſh for euer? It is as poſſible, the word of God ſhould periſh (which ſaith) bleſſed and holy are they that haue their parts in the firſt reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for they ſhall not be hurt of the ſecond death.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 20.6.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19603:19"/>
            <p> I beleeue that ſome of thoſe, whom you affirme borne againe, ſhall periſh; for you affirme you know not what. If ye were guided by God and his trueth, which is his word, you would not affirme any man to be borne of God, except ye were ſure of it verily; nor yet deny any to be borne of God, except ye were as ſure, they are not. But you boldly affirme ſome to be borne againe, which are not; and as boldly denie many that are: in that you iuſtifie your ſelues, and exclude all others from beeing, to you, borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>Wiſedome, if you had harkened vnto her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 2.4.5.6.7.8.9.</note> would haue taught you to haue iudged better. For ſhe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth great vnderſtanding to her children, both ſound and ſure. They doe not iuſtifie that which ſhee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth, nor condemne that which ſhee iuſtifieth. Neither dare her children condemne, though ſhee condemne, except ſhe reueale it vnto them: nor yet iuſtifie, though ſhe iuſtifie: except ſhee declare it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. But if ſhe reueale it, then they dare ſpeake,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18.</note> and what they ſay is done: what they bind is bound, and what they looſe, is looſed.</p>
            <p>But this error of yours, doth ariſe from this falſe ground which you haue laid: namely, that no one may be baptiſed, that is not firſt a new creature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne of the ſpirit, and ſealed therewith: vpon which ground alſo do almoſt all your other errors depend: but I think it is ſufficiently proued already, that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme hath beene adminiſtred by Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, to many Diſciples who were not born again; yet becauſe I will make it more plaine, I will ſet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19603:20"/>downe ſome more examples for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>It is written,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.41.</note> As many as gladly receiued the word, were baptiſed. It is written againe, the thornie ground receiued the word with ioy, therefore the thornie ground was baptiſed. It is euident alſo that the ſtonie ground was baptiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. All theſe were or might be baptiſed.</note> and the high-way-ſide alſo: for they both receiued the word in their hart. And who is not glad of that which he receiueth in his heart? And it is cleere as day (but that men will be ſo wilfully blind) that people were baptiſed preſently, as ſoone as they did beleeue and receiue the word to be a truth, without any further teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of other fruits: as appeareth by the Iayler,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.33.</note> who was preſently baptiſed with all that did belong vnto him. And who is ſo blind, ſo much as to thinke, that they were all inſtantly borne againe, but he that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knew, what it is to be borne againe? I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, here are ten thouſand in England that doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue more,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 8.13.</note> then the moſt of the Iaylers houſhold did beleeue. And what did <hi>Simon Magus</hi> beleeue more, then the Goſpell to bee truth, and many thouſand moe that were baptiſed by the Apoſtles themſelues?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actes</hi> 2.</note> But if you did vnderſtand one thing which was done by the Apoſtles, you ſhould eaſily bee deliuered of this error. And that is this.</p>
            <p>There was a ſecond ſupplie made by the Apoſtles, (after the firſt preaching of the Goſpel, and baptiſing them) whereby they were refined and purified, ſuch of them, as in whom the firſt ſeed of the word tooke deepe root, as appeareth by <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Church of Samaria: who were baptiſed of the holy Ghoſt, by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19603:20"/>the laying on of the hands of the Apoſtle, after they had beleeued and were baptiſed by <hi>Philip.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actes</hi> 8.17.</note> Others alſo that came to the Apoſtles, who had beleeued and beene baptiſed, were afterwards baptiſed of the holy Ghoſt, in the name of Ieſus.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actes</hi> 19.5, 6.</note> And this is it which the Scripture intendeth, which ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16.</note> whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beleeueth and is baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by baptiſme there, the baptiſme of repentance and of the holy Ghoſt. As if the Lord had ſaide, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beleeueth the truth of the Goſpel, and is rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate ſhall be ſaued, Baptiſme cannot be vnderſtood in that place of earthly water, for then <hi>Simon Magus</hi> muſt needes be ſaued, for he beleeued, and was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed with that water.</p>
            <p>And alſo another time there came Certaine Diſciples to the Lord, asking him who ſhouldbe the greateſt in the Kingdome of heauen. The Lord anſwered them to this effect. Doe you come to aske me who is the greateſt in the kingdome of heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.</note> and your ſelues are not ſo much as entred into it yet? Meaning by the kingdome of heauen, that little ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall houſe, whoſe veſſels are all of gold and ſiluer: where is ioy in the holy Ghoſt, and great reſt and peace, not that great houſe which is before deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed: for in that houſe they were already. The Lord takes a little child, and ſets in the middeſt of them. I tell you, ſaith he, though you doe beleeue the truth of my word, and are baptiſed, and be my Diſciples, yet except you become conuerted, and reborne as this little child, you ſhall not ſo much as enter into that kingdome of heauen, wherein I beſtow my ſecrets
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19603:21"/>and greateſt treaſure. Whereby it is euident, as alſo by the other examples, and many moe that might be ſhewed to this purpoſe; that many did beleeue and were baptiſed, before they were returned and became as little children: contrary to your falſe ground Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> whereon dependeth the whole frame of your houſe.</p>
            <p>And if you would but ſearch theſe Scriptures: di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, and compare them together, I hope you ſhould finde theſe things true: and then I truſt you ſhall ſee, that which we now ſee at this preſent, and which may appeare alſo euidently, to all that will weigh thinges vprightly without partialitie, your frame and building pulled downe from the toppe to the bottome,<note place="margin">The outer Court and the Temple.</note> that common things are for the many, and the peculiar things for the few.</p>
            <p>One thing remayneth but not of your building, which you cal the Character and marke of the beaſt, not worthy to come vnder the roofe of your houſe Namely the baptiſing of Children, againſt the which we will ſee and examine what you ſay.</p>
            <p>I haue ſeene a principall anſwer of yours, to an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Circumciſion, to proue the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing of Children: Wherein you deny circumciſion, to be a ſeale or ſigne of the new Couenant, and the righteouſnes therein, of faith: Affirming that it was a ſeale of a carnall couenant made to a carnall ſeede, and calling that carnall Couenant of yours, one of the two teſtaments, and abuſing them by your carnal conceit, who are both of them moſt holy and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.</note> and not carnall as you affirme. And therin you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19603:21"/>ſeeme to your ſelfe, to be ſo wiſe in your application of circumciſion to a carnall couenant, made to a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſeed, that you by meere Ignorance and error to the charge of all, that take it otherwiſe: and ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in all your anſweres and reaſons, this is your principall obiection ſtill, that we miſtake the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and build the baptiſing of children vpon a falſe ground: but herein, by the grace of God, we will ſee who it is that is miſtaken, and that doth erre, and buildeth vpon the ſands. And becauſe that by the miſtaking of the two Teſtaments, and the two ſeeds; and by the falſe diſtinctions them, not onely all your errours, but all other falſe doctrine doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend: as in the true vnderſtanding of them, and right diſtinguiſhing both of the two Teſtaments, and alſo of the two ſeeds all truth doth conſiſt; wee will therfore more carefully by Gods aſſiſtance ſet down what the two Teſtaments are, and alſo diſtinguiſh betweene them: and what the two ſeeds are, and alſo diſtinguiſh betweene them: that ſo we may the more cleerely diſcerne the truth from that which is erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And then we ſhall ſee to which of the two Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Circumciſion doth belong and whether bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme may not be adminiſtred vnto children, as well as Circumciſion was.</p>
            <p>And although baptiſme is nothing, nor vnbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme nothing (as circumciſion is nothing, and vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion nothing) compared with a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor yet is able to pollute any, though he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it in the Church of Rome, and though it bee not worth the contending about, nor yet the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19603:22"/>of, compared with the doctrine of baptiſme, which is regeneration, the waſhing of repentance, and the purging of the holy Ghoſt through Ieſus Chriſt, and faith in him: which is indeed the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of euery liuing ſtone of his Church and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whereof he is the foundation and head ſtone of the corner: becauſe you trouble Iſrael with your flaſhes and falſe lights, affirming from your fleſhly wiſedome, that the baptiſme of children is the marke of the beaſt; we will therefore diſcouer, how you of meere ignorance erre therein, by your miſtaking the two Couenants, and the two Seeds: and how by your falſe diſtinguiſhing both of the two Teſtaments and the two Seeds, you deceiue both your ſelfe and others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Maſter <hi>Smiths</hi> aunſwere.</note>The ſumme of your anſwere is this, Firſt you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the two Teſtaments, but very vntowardly; for you ſay, one was made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Carnall ſeede, and of that Couenant was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion a ſeale.</p>
            <p>Another Couenant was made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſpiritual ſeed, and of that Couenant was the holy ſpirit of promiſe, the ſeale: for the carnall Couenant had a carnall ſeale vpon the carnall ſeede: The ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Couenant had a ſpirituall ſeale vpon the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſeed: and circumciſion which was a carnall ſeale, could not ſeale vp the ſpirituall Couenant to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſeede. The two Teſtaments being thus by you diſtinguiſhed, you goe on to diſprooue the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of children: for we vnder the Goſpell, you ſay, doe not receiue that carnall Couenant which was
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19603:22"/>made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his carnall ſeede, whereof cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was the carnall ſeale, but that carnall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant and ſeale together with the ſubiect of that ſeale (<hi>viz.</hi> a male of eight dayes old) is taken away by Chriſts croſſe. And in the roome thereof, wee haue the ſpirituall Couenant, typed by that carnall Couenant, and the ſpirituall ſeale (<hi>viz.</hi> the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of promiſe) figured by that carnall ſeale: and the ſpirituall infant, <hi>viz.</hi> A new borne babe in Chriſt, in whom Chriſt typed by the male, is newly formed, ſignified by that carnall infant. That all theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars are ſo, you proue it plainely, you ſay, by theſe places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>There are two Teſtaments made with <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24.</note> For <hi>Agar,</hi> that is the olde Teſtament, and <hi>Sara,</hi> that is the new Teſtament, were both married to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> had them both. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>23</label> There are two ſeeds, <hi>Iſhmaell</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Agar,</hi> who typed the carnall ſeed borne after the fleſh: and <hi>Iſaack</hi> of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Sara</hi> typed the ſpirituall ſeede, borne by promiſe.</p>
            <p>There are two ſeales, Circumciſion a ſeale of the carnal children: and the holy ſpirit of promiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 17.11.</note> a ſcale of the ſpirituall couenant, vpon the ſpirituall ſeede.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And as Circumciſion was a ſeale from God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.13.</note> to the carnall ſeed, of the promiſe, and from the carnall ſeed to God in obedience: So the ſpirit of promiſe is a ſeale from God to the ſpirituall ſeed, of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.33</note> and from the ſpirituall ſeede to God in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Theſe thing are euident you ſay, and ſo you proceed to proue and diſproue accordingly.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19603:23"/>
            <p> And here I cannot but meruaile what you meane by this carnall couenant you talke of, which you call one of the two Teſtaments, and of which you make circumciſion the ſeale: and alſo what you meane by <hi>Abrahams</hi> carnall ſeed. Which couenant, ſeale and ſeed you ſay, is taken away, by Chriſts Croſſe. For you ſpeake ſo doubtfully, that one had need dwell in your heart, that would known your meaning. But if you meane as the Scriptures meane which you cite, then it is certaine, you ſay one thing, and meane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. For the Scripture faith, and meaneth thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.22.23.24.25.26.27.28.29.30.31.</note> that <hi>Abraham</hi> had two ſonnes, one by a ſeruant, and one by a free-woman; but hee which was of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, was borne after the fleſh, And hee which was of the free-woman, was borne by promiſe: by the which things another thing is ment, for theſe are the two teſtaments. The one, which is <hi>Agar</hi> of Mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai, which gendereth to bondage (for <hi>Agar</hi> or Sinai is a mountaine in Arabia, and it anſwereth to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falem, which now is, and ſhe is in bondage with her children) But Ieruſalem which is from aboue, is free, which is the mother of vs all, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The meaning is, That as there were two feeds, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the beginning; the ſeed of the ſerpent, and the ſeede of the woman,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 3.15.</note> figured by <hi>Adams</hi> two firſt ſonnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abell,</hi> (<hi>Caine</hi> going before with his ſacrifice, <hi>Abell</hi> comming after with his) The one the ſonne of the ſerpent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the other the childe of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; the one the childe of the lawe of death, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the childe of the Teſtament of life; (for theſe two Teſtaments were before either <hi>Caine</hi> or <hi>Abell</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19603:23"/>came to offer their ſacrifice, and were figured by the two trees that were in the midſt of the Garden:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.9</note> the Tree of knowledge of good and euill, repreſenting the law oftenne commanddements; For to the tenne comandements, &amp; the tree of knowledge of good and euill, one curſe belonged. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.7.</note> Thou ſhalt die the death. And the Tree of life repreſenting the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament and fruite of life, as the Lord himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, when he ſaith, To him that ouercommeth, wil I giue to eate of the tree of life, which is, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the Paradiſe of God.</p>
            <p>And as God did ſet before <hi>Adam,</hi> life and death to chuſe, and he choſe death to himſelfe, and all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16.7.</note> ſo yet ſtill and againe, God hath ſet the ſame before vs, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſaith: Behold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Deut</hi> 30.11.12.14.15.</note> I haue ſet before you life and death, curſe and bleſſing, to chuſe. And as <hi>Adam</hi> choſe death, euen ſo his generation for the moſt part chuſe rather death &amp; curſing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 10.6.7.8.</note> then life and bleſſing; and are the bond-womans children, and ſo will be, like <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay as God did prefigure the two Teſtaments,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.10.12.</note> and the two ſeeds to <hi>Adam,</hi> and his feed vntill <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> So did he then renew his couenants to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> figuring them by <hi>Agar</hi> and <hi>Sara:</hi> and their ſeed by <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaack.</hi> Which thing (me thinks) you M. <hi>Smith</hi> ſhould not be ignorant of, ſeeing you take ſuch great matters vpon you. Now theſe two ſonnes doe not repreſent the naturall Iew,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Iob.</hi> 34.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.34 35.</note> and the naturall Gentile, but the Spirituall Iewe and the Spirituall Gentile, for God reſpects not of what Nation a man be of: ſo he feare and ſeeke him, his couenant ſhall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19603:24"/>be vnto him whereſoeuer he be, as the Apoſtle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14.15.16.26.27.28.29.</note> If the Gentile doe by nature the things contained in the law, that is, be circumciſed in heart, he ſhall be found a Iew: when the Iew circumciſed in skinne, but not in heart, ſhall be found a Gentile. For he is not a Iew that is one without, but hee is a Iew that is one within: and that is not circumciſion that is on the skinne, but that which is in the heart. And theſe are the two ſeedes figured by the two ſonnes, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and are not tyed either to times, or places, or Nations, but are in all times and of all Nations whereſoeuer, leſſe or more.</p>
            <p>Now the mothers of theſe two Children, are ſaid to be <hi>Hagar</hi> that is <hi>Sinai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.</note> and <hi>Sara</hi> that is Sion, Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem from aboue. The one repreſenting the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of commandements, the other the Teſtament of mercy: the one death, the other life; the one cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, the other bleſſing; and theſe are the onely two Teſtaments of God. And whether of theſe two you make circumciſion to be the ſeale or ſigne of, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell. To be a ſeale of the promiſe of life, or of any thing pertaining thereunto, you flatly deny: And to bee a ſeale of the commandements, or of the curſe pronounced with them, Is as contrary as curſing &amp; bleſſing; For circumciſion was giuen to <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as a ſeale of the righteouſnes of faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</note> which God perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not onely vnto him, but to all his ſpirituall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as wel Iewes as Gentiles, not only ſince Chriſts death but long before. Not that circumciſion did ſeale all <hi>Abrahams</hi> naturall Children, to be the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of promiſe: nor yet any one of them, nor <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19603:24"/>himſelfe. But it was giuen as a ſeale, not of their faithfulnes to God, nor yet to ſeale their ſaluation vnto them, but to ſeale God his faithfulnes in his promiſe, to all thoſe of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Children that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardned their hearts like <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</note>, Whether male or female, Iewe or Gentile, which hee ſealed in their hearts by his ſpirit of promiſe, whereby they all cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Abba Father.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And as the rayne-bow doth confirme Gods faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the world, not mans faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to God.</note> Euen as Baptiſme now is a ſeale, not of euery ones ſaluation that receiueth it, but a ſeale of Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, in his Couenant of mercy, made to all <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſeed, baptiſed and circumciſed in heart like him, which he ſealeth vnto their hearts by his ſpirit of promiſe, not by baptiſme: And ſo baptiſme doth come indeed truely in the roome of Circumciſion, not that Circumciſion was a type of baptiſme, but they are both types of one truth: which is Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or baptiſme in heart. As <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Sinai</hi> were of another truth: Euen of the Teſtament of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, which was giuen vpon mount Sinai, which gendreth or increaſeth bondage: Which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to Ieruſalem, &amp; Ieruſalem to it: not becauſe it ſhould be ſo, but becauſe they would bee ſo: Chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather to be <hi>Hagars</hi> ſonnes, Children to <hi>Sinai,</hi> which begetteth and bringeth forth to death:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.16.17.18.19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2.</note> then children of <hi>Sara</hi> and mount Sion, which bringeth forth to life. For as it is written, the Goſpell and word that is preached vnto vs: was alſo preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, but the word which they heard, profited not them, for they when they heard it prouoked him: yet not al; but with whom was he diſpleaſed forty years? euen with thoſe that hardned their hearts, and wold
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19603:25"/>not heare his voice: Euen <hi>Hagars</hi> ſonnes. And as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> cryeth out to them of his tnne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.8.</note> (ſaying) To day if ye wil heare his voice, harden not your hearts, as in the prouocation. For the moſt of all <hi>Abrahams</hi> natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſeed, which poſſeſſed the earthly Ieruſalem, and earthly Canaan, did chuſerather to bee the children of death and bondage, figured by the bond woman and Sinai: Then to be children of life and liberty figured by mount Sion, and the free woman, being all for the moſt part of them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3.</note> ignorant of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of faith, ſought altogether to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſnes, framed according to the Law of commandements (as they pretended) which neither they, nor their fathers did euer keepe: Ioyning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſtrict obſeruation of the Ceremoniall law, ſuppoſing their whole life and ſaluation conſiſted therein, which were both giuen to another end, then that which they intended. For the Law of comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements was giuen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.8.</note> not to the end it ſhold bring any man to ſaluation, by working thereafter, but to make more plaine and manifeſt mans curſed and loſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19.</note> And the law of Ceremonies: As circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Paſcall Lambe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21.</note> The land of Canaan, Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, the Temple, the Altar, the Prieſthood, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and Ceremonies whatſoeuer: Were not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them to the end that in them, and by the obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation of them, they ſhould gaine life and ſaluation: But they were giuen for a time to teach Iſrael the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance contained in the Teſtament of life: And did preach vnto the faithfull ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all land of reſt:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.2.</note> which they entred into by vnharde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19603:25"/>their hearts, and hearing the voice and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of mercy, with all the children of <hi>Hagar,</hi> I meane the vncircumciſed in heart, vtterly reiected, as they doe ſtill to this day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.34.</note> for the ſame generation remaineth ſtill: euen the bond-womans children and their mother alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And I am in feare of you Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> and of your children: for you haue runne your ſelues vpon the ſame rocks with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, iuſtifying your ſelues vpon your carnall obſeruations, framing a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall regeneration and faith, which may faile men like vnto them which put confidence in works, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uations of ceremonies which neuer could ſaue them.</p>
            <p>And as the bondwoman and her children did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and get the vpper hand in the Church of the Iewes, ſo that the bondwoman got the name of the married wife, and of child bearing; and the free woman with her children troden in the duſt, and as a widow forſaken was ſhe accounted, and as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that had neither husband nor children: euen ſo it is now. And as Ieruſalem that then was, did an ſwere to Sinai, and <hi>Hagar,</hi> the mother of bondage: In ſomuch as her children did match theirs in hardneſſe of heart and vnbeliefe, perſecuting the ſonnes of the free woman, as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> did <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Eſau Iacob;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.9. <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.41</note> and as they did in the wilderneſſe, whoſe carcaſes fell: I ſay as Ieruſalem perſecuted the Prophets, and killed them, ſcoffing and deriding the free wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans children: Yea though hee were their King euen <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 23.35 <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.29.30.</note> or Chriſt himſelfe the free womans eldeſt ſonne: and is therefore ſaide to bee in bondage with her children, as <hi>Hagar</hi> was with her ſonne:</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:19603:26"/>
            <p> And as they doing the ſame workes that he did, were caſt out with her ſonne from inheriting the promiſe, with the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the free woman: euen ſo it is now. For the Serpents ſeed is yet aliue, the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman hath many ſonnes, though the free woman hath few or none to be ſeene. <hi>Iſmaels</hi> brethren haue had the vpper hand a great while, euen among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as they had among the Iewes. And their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath the praiſe of child-bearing ſtill, as ſhee had then. And Ieruſalem from aboue, the free woman and her children: deſpiſed and troden vpon (like a ſtreete) as they were wont to be,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 11.2.</note> by ſuch like obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and Phariſaicall boaſters, who pretend obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſacrifice, as much as euer did they: who are likewiſe in moſt curſed bondage, and muſt alſo bee caſt out with them, and ſhall not inherit with the free-womans children, nor enter into reſt with them</p>
            <p>But leruſalem from aboue is free, As ſhe euer was from the beginning, and is the mother of vs all: euen of <hi>Abell, Henoch, Abraham, Dauid,</hi> the Prophets, the Apoſtles, and all that euer are and ſhall bee ſaued. And although ſhee be as no body, and no where, in compariſon:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5 4.1.</note> Yet as <hi>Eſaiah</hi> ſaid vnto her in his daies, and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid vnto her in his time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.27.</note> ſo be it ſaid now, and ſtill. Reioyce thou barren that beareſt no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, breake forth and cry in ioy, thou that beareſt not: for the deſolate hath many moe children then ſhe that hath an husband. And this is the trueth of the matter.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the two Teſtaments, And theſe are the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19603:26"/>two ſeeds: To wit, the law of Commaundements, giuen vppon mount Sinai, which gendereth to death and bondage, And the law of life giuen on mount Sion, which gendereth to reſt and liberty. And the curſed generation of <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Iſmaell,</hi> the ſeede of the one, and the bleſſed generation of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> and <hi>Iſaack,</hi> the ſeede of the other. And ſo the Scriptures and truth is the ſame, from the beginning to the end of the world. And the two Teſtaments do remaine ſtill: yea, euen that Teſtament figured by <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Sinai,</hi> and the children of bondage figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by her ſonne. And the curſe alſo doth ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, and is not taken away by the Croſſe of Chriſt from any of <hi>Hagars</hi> children. But onely from the children of <hi>Sara</hi> the faithfull ſeede. And Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, was not a ſeale, nor ſigne, of any other coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant whatſoeuer, but of the Circumciſion of the heart, and the righteouſneſſe of faith and mercy, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenanted firſt to <hi>Adam,</hi> then to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo from time to time renewed: And at laſt confirmed by the Mediator himſelf, and by his death vpon the Croſſe: who hath made all things cleare and manifeſt vnto vs, if we had but ſpirituall eies to ſee them. But hee came to ſaue and to ſeeke out all the loſt ſheepe, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ninety and nine: euen all <hi>Hagars</hi> proude ſounes, who thought them ſelues wiſe and ſafe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: Euen ſo now. This is the iudgement which the Lord hath ſent into the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.39.</note> and it is meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſeene this day. The blinde doe ſee, and they that ſee are made blinde. Not the rich nor the full, but the poore and the empty, receiue the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19603:27"/>
            <p> And now Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> whereas you would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſproue the argument drawne from circumciſion, to proue the baptiſing of children, by your doubtfull ſpeech of miſtaking the couenant, and by your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound diſtinguiſhing the two Teſtaments, which is your firſt and principall ground, whereon many of your other reaſons doe depend, It may now be well ſeene, that you are the man, that doe miſtake. For I pray you tell me, where you will beſtowe circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and of what Teſtament will you make it a ſeale? If you take it away from the new I eſtament made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed by promiſe? Will ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe it on the law of commaundements giuen on mount Sinai, and the ſonnes therof? I pray you then, which doth it ſeale vnto them? perfect holineſſe which they neuer had, but altogether the contrary: Or did it ſeale the curſe, which ſaith, Curſed is euery one that continueth not in all theſe thinges to doe them: which indeede moſt iuſtly did belong to all ſuch ſeruants to ſinne, and bondage, and rebels to grace: As all <hi>Abrahams</hi> carnall ſeede, borne after the fleſh were. I think you dare not affirme any of theſe: But it ſhould ſeeme you meane, it ſealed a bleſſing vnto the carnall ſeed, and not a curſe.</p>
            <p>Say you ſo M. <hi>Smith,</hi> Then where are you now? you haue left the olde Teſtament; For therein lieth no bleſſing. But curſed is euery man by (that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous law) the olde Teſtament. Take heede, make not another Teſtament, two is all. What carnall couenant doe you meane, The Scriptures neuer told vs yet of a carnall couenant. The two Teſtaments
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19603:27"/>of God are both holy &amp; ſpirituall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.</note> as the Scriptures witneſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.16.</note> Indeede there were carnall commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, rites and ſhadowes, belonging a while as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and Miniſters to the new Teſtament, teaching and preaching Chriſt Ieſus: which are called Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, impotent, and beggerly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9.</note> in regarde of their weakeneſſe leaneneſſe &amp; pouerty. Yet the beſt means that then was to teach Chriſt, till Chriſt himſelfe came. And were euen as a bondage, yea to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed, compared with after times: yet great thinges were taught by them, though very darkly and weakly. But when the ſubſtance came, ſhadowes were caſt away. They are blinde men, that can goe as well by night as by day. The day is come, the night is paſt, the true light now ſhineth. Who doe not walke therein, but blinde men? yet they ſay they ſee, and therefore their ſinne remaines; Night birds they are, and cannot ſee by day. The day-ſtarre neuer roſe in their hearts. And Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> though ſhadowes be gone, the ſubſtance ſtill remaines. The two Teſtaments are both whole and ſound as euer they were,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.17.18.19.</note> and ſtill continue in their ſtrength and force. And the children of curſing and bleſſing doe ſtill continue. And whoſoeuer they were, in any age or time, that put confidence in workes of any kinde whatſoeuer: Either thoſe contained in the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, or any other letter, ſacrifice, or cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, or any other religious exerciſe, except the promiſe: were all in bondage, and were children to <hi>Hagar.</hi> And alſo whoſoeuer he be, and when, and whereſoeuer, ſince Chriſt: that puts truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19603:28"/>in works, whether workes of the law, or of the Goſpell, or any ceremony, or ſhaddow, or religious exerciſe whatſoeuer, or knowledge, or faith, except the promiſe of mercy and loue in Chriſt Ieſus: He, or they, whatſoeuer, ſhal befound the bond-womans children, of the race of <hi>Came</hi> and <hi>Iſmael,</hi> and inherite not with the heyres of promiſe.</p>
            <p>And as then, before Chriſt, Ieruſalem that ſhould haue beene free, whoſe children boaſted much of their freedome: and in his daies and the Apoſtles time alſo, euen till her deſtruction, was in bondage with her children: euen ſo Ieruſalem that now is; who boaſteth (as much as they could do) of her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, riches, and fulneſſe; I meane the great and famous Church of Chriſtians through the world, fulfilling her workes, anſwering vnto her, as ſhee did vnto <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> and <hi>Sinai,</hi> is alſo in bondage with her children. Onely Ieruſalem from aboue, with all her children; is free, though her name be hid, and her face couered with duſt: Ariſe thou captiue daughter Sion, and put on thy garment of beauty, for thy day is euen at hand.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 54.7.</note> 
               <hi>For a little while in his anger, he hid his face from thee, but with euer lasting mercy will he embrace thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tell me yet, was the ceremoniall law, the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall couenant you meane, that you ſay circumciſion is the ſeale of? For I would willingly ſearch out all your holes, and not leaue you one to runne into: will ye ſay ſo? Is it poſſible that a Ceremony, can be the ſeale of a Ceremony, or of Ceremonies? For I truſt you agree that Circumciſion is a Ceremonie, and did belong and make one with the reſt: What great
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19603:28"/>thing was there in that law (beſides the promiſe of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of ſinnes) that Circumciſion was a ſeale of? for indeede the whole ceremoniall lawe, may as well be called a Ghoſpell as a Law, inſomuch as it wholly intended Chriſt, and the whole truth in him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.40. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.44. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5.</note> And therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> is commaunded to make and order all things, according to the patterne which hee ſaw in the Mount; and ſo Circumciſion was a ſeale of the promiſe and righteouſneſſe of faith, not onely to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but to all <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeede, both male and female, Iew and Gentile: Howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in their ſpiritual generation, there is neither male nor female, Iew nor Gentile,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</note> but they are all one Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine and Spouſe of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Miſtake me not in my former ſpeech, as if I enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to make another Goſpell of the law of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, but I call it ſo, becauſe it ſerued the Goſpell, and kept aſchoole (as it were) to teach Chriſt: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaid, they were vnder Tutors vntill the time appointed of the father;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.2.</note> neither is it another Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beſides thoſe two Teſtaments which are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed before, but was a ſhaddowing law, attending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chriſt, vntill he had offered vp himſelfe, which muſt all then vaniſh: but the two Teſtaments are firme and ſtable, ſpirituall, holy, and endure, as I haue ſaid before.</p>
            <p>But to the matter againe, for tenne to one Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> will runne to the land of Canaan, and take it for his refuge: but if you doe, truely it will leaue you in the ſame diſtreſſe, that you were in before, for it is no land of reſt for you now: But tell me, was it the carnall Couenant you talke of?</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19603:29"/>
            <p> If you remember, in the beginning of your anſwer, ſhewing your skill in the origmals, yet prouing your ſelfe very ignorant in the two Teſtaments, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by your diſtinguiſhing them, you ſay, the two Couenants or two Teſtaments, for ſo you ſay: Tell me doe you meane the two Teſtaments, which the Scripture doth ſet forth, and ſo often tell vs of? And I pray you, was the land of Canaan one of theſe two Teſtaments, becauſe the land of Canaan was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeede? Is it therefore one of the two Teſtaments? If you will make euery promiſe that is in the Scriptures a ſeuerall Teſtament, you diſtinguiſh faire, you wil haue a hundred Teſtaments then at leaſt: And is this the Teſtament, Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion did ſeale to the carnall ſeede? What was the reaſon then they were caried into Babylon captiues? It ſhould ſeeme by your ſaying, that God had forgot his Couenant quite, for they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> carnall ſeede (as you meane by carnall) euery one of them: Let me tell you, They were not carried thither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not carnall,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 36.15, 26, 17.</note> but becauſe they were not ſpirituall, they circumciſed their ſonnes then in Babylon, and doe ſtill to this day: Are they ſo blinde as you, to thinke that circumciſion dooth ſeale the land of Canaan vnto them? Indeede it may well be, for they are very blinde, although experience might haue taught them otherwiſe long ere this day. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the land of Canaan was promiſed <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeede, and they were ſet in poſſeſſion thereof with a ſtrong hand: but with what condition was that inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance giuen them, and for whoſe ſakes? Had it not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19603:29"/>been for <hi>Abraham</hi> his faithful one, &amp; his ſpiritual ſeed <hi>Iacob</hi> his beloued, they ſhould neuer haue poſſeſſed that land,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.37.38. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.3.4.5.</note> God would neuer haue caſt out the Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites for Eſaues and Iſmalites, but to Iacob his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, he ſaith, I haue giuen Nations for thee, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for thy ſake: And what was the condition? ſurely the keeping of his couenants and walking in his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies; I doe not meane the perfect keeping of the ten commaundements,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 23.16.</note> giuen in two Tables of ſtone, that fiery couenant which neither they nor their fathers were able to beare, for therby the beſt of them were found euen as a bryer, and the moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous like a thorne, but the teſtament and couenant that he made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he ſaide, I will bee they God, and the God of thy ſeede for euer, not his carnall ſeede, but his ſpirituall ſeede: not conſiſting of one Nation but of many Nations, whereof God made him a Father, commaunding him to keepe it, ſaying, thou ſhalt keepe my couenants, thou and thy ſeed: And this ſhall be a ſigne (ſaith he) of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betweene you and me: namely circumciſion, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying thereby that if they vnhardened their hearts and harkened to his voice, and Couenant of mercy and loue that he had made to him: taking him for their God and louing him, truſting him, and putting their confidence in him: which is the righteouſnes of faith. Then they ſhould inherit the land and poſſeſſe it for euer, and many bleſſings more they ſhould haue they ſhould ſleepe laſe and dwell in peace, a Citie of peace they ſhould haue, no enemy ſhould euer hurt them: and not onely ſo, but reſt to their ſoules alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13.14.15.16.</note>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:19603:30"/>they ſhoulde haue, and peace which is the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing<note n="*" place="margin">By their earthly Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſpirtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Canaan, the land of the liuing.</note> Canaan, the land of the bleſſed, the Citie of peace. But if they hardened their hears, and reſiſted his uoice, deſpiſing his couenant of grace and fauour Iuſtifying themſelues as their Fathers did in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, of whom God ſaith, I haue ſeen this people &amp; behold it is a ſtiffnecked people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.8 9.</note> wherefore God was angrie and ſaide to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 32.10</note> when he prayed for them, let me alone, for I will conſume them. But I wil make of thee a mighty Nation, I ſay if thus they ſhould harden their hearts, and ſtiffen their necks, and deſpiſe his couenant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.16, 17, 18, 19.</note> then curſed at home and curſed abroad, and his mercies ſhould depart from them, and as hee ſware in his wrath, that they which prouoked him in the wildernes with their ſtiffe and ſtubborne hearts, ſhould not enter into his reſt neither earthly norhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly: So they prouoking him in like maner, though they were in poſſeſſion of that land of Canaan, (ſhould neither inherit nor enter into the ſpirituall Canaan therby intended) nor inioy it in peace, but be deſtroyed and carried captiue into other Nations, and their Countrie and Citie taken as a prey of the Heathen:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leui.</hi> 16.31, 32.</note> And as the little ſpirituall ſtocke of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſeed, were kept fortie yeares long in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, from poſſeſſing the land for <hi>Hagars</hi> ſtiffnecked childrens ſakes: So poore <hi>Daniell</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahs</hi> little ſpirituall houſe, were carried captiue for the wicked Cananites ſakes, and alſo for that they were as good to liue ſeruants in a ſtrange land, as be murdered and perſecuted for the trueth and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe at home, for in Babylon they found more
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19603:30"/>grace, and fauour for their truth and wiſedome, yea euen with Kings, then they found at home, and alſo for that by affliction, they were brought home from ſecurity to repentance: But God remembring his promiſe made to <hi>Abraham</hi> his ſeruant, after hee had corrected and reſined them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ievem.</hi> 29.10.</note> brought them home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and reſtored them vnto their former ſtate. But within a while, the ſonnes of <hi>Hagar</hi> encreaſing, his mercies were forgotten: and his Prophets went to wrack againe, and the Iſrael of God troden in the duſt, vntill the Meſſiah came, which is called Chriſt, who ſet his feete vpon that holy Mount, and walked in the ſtreetes of his Citie of peace, bewailing the diſobedience of <hi>Abrahams</hi> children in the fleſh, cried out, Oh Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37.</note> thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that were ſent vnto thee, How oft, ſaith hee, how oft would I haue gathered thy children together, as a Hen doth her Chrickens vnder her wings, and you would not.</p>
            <p>Beloued, ſaith he, thy houſe is left vnto thee deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, for thine enemies ſhall caſt a banke about thee, and keepe thee in on euery ſide. And wherefore now was it Maſter <hi>Smith?</hi> euen becauſe they would not vnharden their hearts, repent and heare his voice, ſo often crying and calling vnto them by his Prophets from time to cime, who ſtill proceede in wickedneſſe notwithſtanding, and fulfilled the works of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the higheſt degree, and yet could ſay, garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the Tombes of the Prophets, which their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had killed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.29.</note> Oh if wee had liued in the dayes of our Fathers, wee would not haue done this, and yet
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19603:31"/>they could take that great Prophet and Prince of the couenant, and kill him, ſtoning and killing his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles alſo: and therefore, I ſay, and for that cauſe it was, that Ieruſalem was made deſolate, and the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple burnt with fire, and not a ſtone left vpon a ſtone vncaſt down, whereas otherwiſe if they had heard his voice, and would haue beene gathered together like <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeede, and not haue reſiſted, but embraced and kept his couenant and righteouſneſſe of faith, which circumciſion did ſignifie vnto them, they had beene a Nation vntill this day, and their land had yeelded her fruite vnto them, their City had beene a City of peace till now, and their Temple vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defaced: But becauſe they refuſed, downe with it, downe with it, euen to the very ground. Deface it for euer, let their table bee made a ſnare, and bow thou downe their back alway.</p>
            <p>And now Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> whither will you goe to reſt your ſelfe, Canaan is taken from you, Ieruſalem is deſolate; there is no abiding place for you any longer, you haue beene there a great while: Will ye reſt you at Amſterdam in Holland? Indeede there was a people once, not many yeeres agoe, which came to Amſterdam, with their wiues and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in ſhips, with this beliefe and reſolution, that Holland was the land of Canaan, and Amſterdam Ieruſalem, and therefore there they would inhabite. I hope you are not of their minde therein, as they were of your minde concerning baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Although Amſterdam &amp; Holland doe entertaine all ſects of ſeuerall opinions, ſuffering them there in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19603:31"/>reſt and peace: Yet is not Holland that land of reſt, nor Amſterdam that City of peace: but if ye will be ſafe indeede, and finde reſt and peace to your ſoules, Fly to mount Sion, and to the City of the liuing God, the caeleſtiall Icruſalem, and to the company of innumerable Angels, and to the aſſembly &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the firſt borne, which are all written in heauen, and to God the Iudge of all, and to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of iuſt and perfect men, and to Ieſus the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the new teſtament, and to the bloud of ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that ſpeaketh better things then that of <hi>Abell,</hi> whoſe bloud cried vp to heauen (not for mercy and pardon) but for iuſtice and wrath againſt <hi>Caine,</hi> his naturall elder brother, but indeed <hi>Iſmaels</hi> eldeſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in euill he was.</p>
            <p>And now I hope by this time you ſee what the two teſtaments are, and alſo what the law of ceremonies were, &amp; what the land of Canaan and Ieruſalem did intend, and to whom it was promiſed, and for whoſe ſakes it was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for an inheritance, &amp; for whoſe ſins, &amp; for what ſins it was made deſolate: you haue ſeene alſo the two teſtaments truly diſtinguiſhed, and the two ſeeds alſo, and what they are, according to the meaſure of grace, which God hath giuen me. I hope you ſee alſo, that circumciſion did not ſeale the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements to any, nor yet the curſe that went with them, nor yet the law of ceremonies, nor yet did it ſeale the land of Canaan &amp; Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the carnal ſeed: But it ſigned &amp; ſealed the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that was deliuered to <hi>Abraham</hi> in theſe words:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17.18.</note> Thou ſhalt bee a Father of many Nations, which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19603:32"/>could not be vnderſtood of a carnall but of a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſeede. And I will bee thy God ſaith hee, and the God of thy ſeede after thee, meaning that ſeede which ſhould walke before him and bee vpright, as was and did their father <hi>Abraham:</hi> and keepe his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 17.1</note> circumciſing not the skin but their hearts, the true ſeale of the righteouſnes of faith, confirmed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by the ſpirit of promiſe, ſignified by that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the skin: And then he would giue them not onely the land of Canaan, but that Canaan of Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the land of true and perfect reſt, for an euerlaſting poſſeſſion, and be their God for euermore.</p>
            <p>And now tell vs Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> why may not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of the element of water, be adminiſtred to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (as well as circumciſion) being but a rudiment as circumciſion was? If <hi>Timothy</hi> might be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, to no end but to pleaſe the Iewes, in hope to winne ſome of them: why may not children be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with this hope, and to this end, that they might become Chriſtians and be borne againe. If a ſonne that was at the point of death, was reſtored to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect health at the requeſt of his father, that beleeued by the power of Chriſt: why ſhould not children bee baptiſed, at the requeſt of their parents which beleeue, by the hands of his ſeruants, ſeeing that baptiſme is neither able to heale a body nor yet to ſaue a ſoule. Indeede ſeruants are very apt to thinke themſelues wiſer then their maſters: for when they brought lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children to Chriſt, his Diſciples being very igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (then) of the Lords bountie: forbad them that brought them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.13.</note> diſdaining that a little child which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19603:32"/>they thought capable of nothing, ſhould be brought to Chriſt, as if he would regard it: whereas the Lord contrary to their expectation rebuking them, ſaide, Suffer little children to come vnto mee and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the kingdome of heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.13, 14 15, 16.</note> and laying his moſt holy hands vpon them, bleſſed them.</p>
            <p>And here I would know of you Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> whether the hands of Chriſt, were not more holie then any water in England or Holland, and whether the bleſſing he beſtowed one thoſe children, were not greater then any grace or bleſſing, that water with your hands and words can conferre to any: on whomſoeuer you can beſtow it? I thinke you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and all men elſe, that Chriſts hands were holier and his bleſſings greater: If then children were capable of the greater, why not then of the leſſer? If Chriſt made choice of a little child before all other, to repreſent and ſigne forth the conuerſion and new birth, which baptiſme alſo doth prefigure and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, why may not theſe two ſignes well and lawfully be ioyned together, ſeeing they are both as Preachers of one truth: you wil haue a child capable of the mark and Character of the beaſt: and yet you wil not haue it capable of the Elementiſh baptiſme: againe you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the forme of baptiſme vſed in England, but you call it the marke of the beaſt, onely becauſe it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to a little child, whom you compare to a tree, a mad-man and a foole: And thereby it doth follow, that the marke of the beaſt doth wholy depend in the child for the forme you iuſtifie: The matter which you call the child, you onely condemne, and lay to it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19603:33"/>charge, that it doth receiue an indelible marke of the beaſt. A lacke poore child, thou haſt a worſe enemie now then the diſciples, who forbad thee to come to Chriſt? What a monſter would you make of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle water, and a litle child, ſhall I tell you Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> if this be the marke of the beaſt, you are the beaſt: for there is no beaſt in the world, doth giue this marke, but you and your fellow Anabaptiſts.</p>
            <p>And as I ſaid before,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3</note> if <hi>Timothy</hi> might be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, after circumciſion was aboliſhed by the Croſſe of Chriſt, at which time whoſoeuer receiued circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion as a thing neceſſary to ſaluation, depriued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wholy of the benefit of Chriſt: I ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2.</note> if <hi>Timothy</hi> were circumciſed, being a Chriſtian, one to whom it belonged, not onely to pleaſe the Iewes in hope to win ſome of them, and yet ſinned not:</p>
            <p>How dare you thenlay this heauy burthen vpon a child (although baptiſme did not belong to it as you ſay) that it cannot bee baptiſed but it receiueth the marke of the beaſt, and is culpable of the wrath of God, and to be tormented in fire and brimſtone for euermore: poore children, if this bee true, vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py be you aboue all creatures; ſeeing ſo many of you die in your infancy, with the marke vpon you vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, for which you ſhall be tormented in hell fire and brimſtone, whereof ye are as innocent as the child vnborne. O miſerable law and miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, God forbid it ſhould bee ſo: rather the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker if he repent not, ſhall be caſt with all ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of lies, into the lake of fire and brimſtome, which is the ſecond death.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:19603:33"/>
            <p> What a Iew Maſter <hi>Smith?</hi> and worſe then a Iew, what a law maker? and a law of bondage aboue all bondage: O touch not, wet not, eate not, death is at the dore. What? ſuch a great man as you, afraid of bug-beares: Ah Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> giue ouer childrens play now: you are a man, and a man that ſhould bee wiſe. Conſider things rightly: be not ſo haſty, ſay lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle but ſay well: learne to come like one of theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.15.</note> whome you condemne: weepe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for your ſinnes, and ſcorne it not: Be meeke and of a lowly heart, and diſdaine it not: forbid not little children to be baptiſed with water on the Skinne: of whom you ought to learne to be baptiſed in heart. be mercifull to all and bountifull, as God is bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full who giueth his ſunne to ſhine vnto the good, and the bad, and the raine of his worde, to fall vpon the iuſt, and vniuſt: To teach you and me and all of vs what we ſhould doe. The ſpirit ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22.17.</note> whoſoeuer wil, let him come. Take you heed, adde not to, nor diminiſh from his word, giue to all that come, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you haue power to giue. Chriſt gaue a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing to little children, laying his owne handes vpon them, ſeeing their parents came ſo willingly &amp; requeſted him: them parents can now looke for at the hands of baptiſme, when they come bringing their children and requeſt it. Imbrace little children therefore, and though you cannot giue them the greater, giue them the leſſer. Did the Lord compare his little returned ones to a little child, and dare you compare that child, to a ſtone, and a ſtocke, a tree, a mad man and a foole, and ſay it is as lawfull to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19603:34"/>the one as the other. If you had liued in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles daies &amp; had bin one of them, you wold haue bin glad if the Iewes, or heathen, had come to you with willing minds to haue their children baptiſed, to this end, that they might looſe the name of a Iew, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and be called a Chriſtian. But now it is ſo ſtale it ſtinckes with you Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> you are ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witcht with this opinion, that baptiſme with water doth giue an entrance into the ſpeciall kingdome of Heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> (which the Lord ſpeaketh of, when he ſaith, Except ye returne and become as little children, yee ſhal not enter into the kingdome of heauen) that you runne into a hundred errors:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5.</note> Whereas regeneration onely is the entrance into that kingdome of heauen; where into none come, but ſuch as ſhall bee ſaued: And whereas baptiſme of water, giues but an entrance into the common Kingdome of heauen:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.47.</note> compared to a net which catcheth fiſh of all ſorts, good and bad,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.45.</note> and the bad haue as much grace confer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnto them by that baptiſme as the good,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22.</note> as they haue of his Sunne and raine: for the bad are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more ful of knowledge by the light, and can diſcourſe more redily vpon the word of God, then the good. <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apollo</hi> may water, but it is God by the Spirit of regeneration,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</note> that giues the increaſe.</p>
            <p>Are you Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> and your company, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wiſedome? and diſcerne ye not, neither do ye iuſtifie theſe things. Are you a teacher in Iſraell, and know not what it is to be borne againe? Are ye thoſe wiſe and prudent men of vnderſtanding, from whom
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19603:34"/>theſe things are hidden, that are reuealed vnto babes? Is it not giuen to you to know the ſecrets of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, what hath God forgot himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25 <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11.</note> are you that Ieruſalem from aboue, and are theſe things hidden from you, doth he not giue to his little ones, great things? Is hee not the ſame to day, that hee was yeſterday, and ſhall he not be the ſame to morrow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? Yea hee is the ſame for euer: and beholde I am with you (ſaith he) vnto the worlds end,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>John</hi> 14.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> though Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth doe paſſe away, yet his word ſhall not paſſe away vnfulfilled.</p>
            <p>Beleeue ye not this? I know ye beleeue it, And I hope better of you, though I ſo ſpeake; for God hath enlarged my heart, and opened my mouth vnto you, which putteth me in great hope, that you are of that remnant which ſhall be ſaued. But yet a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for I haue ſomewhat more to ſay vnto you which is hard to be vttered, becauſe I ſay, ye are dull of hearing, and becauſe it would take vp much time to ſet downe all wherein you miſſe, and alſo it being a courſe wherin I take no pleaſure, I wil rather ſet downe what is the truth, then tell of your falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, that by the grace of God beleeuing the one, we may eſcape the other.</p>
            <p>Now if you will know what difference there is yet more betweene the true Spouſe and Church of Chriſt, which he doth build himſelfe, againſt which, the gates of hell ſhal not preuaile, nor yet the ſecond death, to whom he hath giuen the keyes of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, and thoſe her entercommoners, I will tell you.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:19603:35"/>
            <p> Firſt let vs conſider how things were in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes on earth, for then I am ſure, truth was in place and practiſe both, and I wil not labour to make it agree with theſe weake times: but much rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and deſire, that we which liue in theſe corrupt times, might agree with, and become like it. I ſay, whoſoeuer then gladly receiued the word (as it is written) were baptiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1.</note> and were called of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles generally by the names of holy brethren, parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the heauenly vocation, &amp;c. Inſomuch as they were made partakers of the holy Ghoſt, and conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to that heauenly calling,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4.5, 6: <hi>Heb.</hi> 10,29.</note> being enlightened &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of that heauenly gift: were called holy, in regard of theſe good beginnings, which was wrought in them, whereby their olde life was reformed. (And therefore the Lord compareth them that receiue the ſeed of his word, ſome to the high way ſide, ſome to ſtonie ground, and ſome to thornie ground, &amp; ſome to good ground which brought forth fruite: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they were ſanctified and purged of ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe of ſpirit:) wherefore they are ſaid (by the Lord) to be ſwept and garniſhed: and (by <hi>Peter</hi>) ſaid to be waſhed, and to the Hebrewes ſanctified: and all this is wrought in them by the miniſtration of the good word of God, which they had taſted of, and by the operation of the holy Ghoſt whereof they were made partakers, whereby alſo ſome of them wrought miracles, and ſome caſt out diuels.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things are all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon,<note place="margin">Except the good fruite.</note> as well to thoſe vncircumciſed in heart, the vnregenerate: As to the circumciſed in heart, the little ones, borne againe.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19603:35"/>And although theſe things be effected by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the word and of the holy Ghoſt, and do tend to his kingdome; (for the Lord doth nothing againſt his owne kingdome any more, then Sathan doth worke againſt his kingdome) yet it is not regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 26. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3,5.</note> the birth of water and the holy Ghoſt, ſpoken of, nor yet the firſt reſurrection; And though this ſowing of the word of the Lord, and theſe effects of the ſpirit do tend to the kingdom, yet is it not ſowen in the high wayes, nor in the ſtonie ground, nor in the thornie ground, to the end it ſhould bring forth fruit like the good ground, Thirty, ſixty, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold. And although theſe foure ſorts of ground, are Communicants in theſe commons together, and little difference can be diſcerned betweene them, by theſe firſt effects and beginnings, for the raine doth fall on all, and the Sunne ſhines without reſpect.</p>
            <p>Yet when the fruite doth appeare after this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall blade,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 4, 28.</note> whereby the good ground is knowne from the bad, as the wheat is from the tares, and after this generall raine and ſun-ſhine, the good ground, like good trees, doth bring forth good fruit: There doth appeare ſo great a difference betweene them, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene end and beginning, betweene firſt and laſt: betweene the blade, and the fruite: Betweene the kingdome compared to a Net, wherein all ſorts of fiſh is caught, both good and bad; and the kingdom compared to a field, wherein lay a treaſure hid of ſo great worth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.44.</note> that whoſoeuer could get poſſeſſion of it (though it coſt him all that euer hee had, if it were neuer ſo much) yet ſhould his gaine be great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19603:36"/>And betweene thoſe little ones (who are borne againe) whoſe loue is great, for great reſpects: Who know they are tranſlated from death to life; And thoſe vnreturned ones,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14.15.</note> that loue not, nor know whether they goe. And as the difference is great, in regard of the vncertainty of the one, and the certaine euerlaſting happineſſe of the other: So haue they, a Charter ſo great, and freedome ſo ſtrong, with ſo many priuiledges belonging thereunto, as no Citie in the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.</note> nor kingdome can afford the like.</p>
            <p>And wherein, thoſe entercommoners, on whom God hath ſhewed his bounty, in giuing them Sunne and raine, and haue not yet brought forth fruit, can haue no part nor fellowſhip: neither ought (any more) to preſume to touch or meddle with, then thoſe that might not touch nor ſtay the Arke: or him to whom <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, thou haſt no part nor fellowſhip with vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.21.</note> nor in this adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>But thoſe poore, little, rich, fruitfull ones, are the onely Prieſts of God, the ſtay and pillars of his Arke of Arks: not made of wood,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.5.6.</note> which now is gone to wrack, but of heauenly enduring matter, and trees of life: and although they be the pillars and ſtayes of it, yet are they not the builders: But the Lord alone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 3.12.</note> (who ſaith) vpon this rock will I build my Church.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now as theſe fruitfull trees, and free-borne Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, doe pertake, and haue fellowſhip together, in the priuiledges peculiar to this holy Church &amp; City of God;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> being (as one ſaith) a choſen generation, a royall Prieſthood, an holy Nation, a people ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: So do they ſhew forth the vertues of him that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19603:36"/>hath called them, whoſe loue is perfect in them: whereby they know each other to be borne of God (as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith) Hereby we know that ye are in him.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.5.</note> And as theſe are knowne, either to other, by their fruit, which fruit I will not ſpeake of heere, ſeeing it is as I thinke plainly deſcribed before: So out of the great heape of Commoners, doe ſometimes appeare euill trees, who are knowne alſo to thoſe that are borne againe by their euill fruit, the fruit of death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.43.14.</note> to be vncurable euill trees. That is, ſo ſeene againſt the light, and them that walke in it, as that they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, the ſentence of eternall death, euen while they liue, trees twiſe dead,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</note> and pluckt vp by the rootes: of whom it is written, Let him be curſed.</p>
            <p>And as the good ground or trees, do not appeare all at once, out of the generall field of Commoners: but when it pleaſeth him who giueth the encreaſe, ſome ſooner, ſome later: So, no more doe the euill trees appeare all at once, but now, and then, when their euill fruite is ripe; ſome breake forth betimes, ſome ſtay longer, ſome not at all, (to the Church I meane) vntill the great day of account: who then ſhall be found ſpeechleſſe, without the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And as the euill ſeruant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.8.</note> that hid his Maſters talent: And as the fiue fooliſh virgins, who found no oyle in their lamps when the bridegroome came, ſuppoſing till then, all was well: Euen ſo likewiſe, is there many of his beloued ones, not knowne to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (but the Lord himſelfe) vntill that day: who then, with the reſt of their fellowes, ſhall bee made manifeſt to all: yea, euen to thoſe, who ſhall then
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19603:37"/>admire their glory and riches, when themſelues ſhall lye in duſt, and ſhame. So that when the Lord ſaith in his Parable:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.26.27.</note> That when the wheat did appeare by the fruit, then did alſo appeare the tares: his meaning is, not that in the generall kingdome all the wheat appeares at once, and all the tares; but as I haue ſaid before. And therefore the ſeruants, muſt not goe to weeding at the firſt ſprout of the eare, though ſome wheat, and ſome tares doe euidently appeare, leaſt they plucke vp wheat with tares. For ſome of both ſhall remaine vnknowne vnto them, vntill the great harueſt day. And this is, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋer. </seg>30</label> and ſhall be the condition of the common field, &amp; vniuerſity of Chriſtians vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that day: and therefore the ſeruants muſt ſpare to iudge or iuſtifie, till their fruits doe euidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. And as the Sunne doth ſhine, and the raine doth fall equally vpon them, I meane thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that ſhall proue tares; as thoſe that ſhall prooue good wheat,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44.45.</note> fit for the Lords owne barne: So ought alſo his ſeruants to be kind to the vnkinde, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to all. Inſomuch as in the firſt effects before mentioned, there doth appeare little or no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p>Now hauing thus diſtinguiſhed, betweene Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Chriſtian, Kingdome and Kingdome, tree and tree: Let vs ſee how matters doe fall out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, and how they doe agree: and alſo how they ought to walke and carrie themſelues toward each other. And that we may the eaſier accompliſh our purpoſe, we will deuide theſe great company of Chriſtians into two parts, that is to ſay:</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:19603:37"/>
            <p> Some borne of God, returned and become as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children, to whom he hath giuen the keyes of the kingdome, and all thoſe priuiledges before ſpoken of, and a thouſand treaſures more beſides, on whom the ſecond death ſhall neuer haue power, nor the gates of hell preuaile. The other vnregenerate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall partakers with the regenerate, in all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon firſt thinges before mentioned, but not in the ſecond effects the laſt and ſpeciall things.</p>
            <p>Now, theſe kinde of brethren, doe often times of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the little ones, and deſpiſe them: becauſe they are little in their owne eyes, and poore in their own ſpirit, and are returned and become as little children, &amp; becauſe their fruits of loue appeare beyond theirs, knowing their owne works to be euill, and their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good, wherefore the Lord ſaith to thoſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10.11.12.</note> Take heed that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones, theſe loſt ſheepe whom I haue ſought out; for I ſay vnto you, howſoeuer you eſteeme of them, Their Angels ſtand alwaies beholding my Fathers face who is in heauen. Nay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>3</label> except ye returne (ſaith the Lord) (to thoſe Diſciples who would ſo faine know who ſhould be the greateſt) and become as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdome of heauen. But whoſoeuer is become humble as a little childe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>4</label> they are the greateſt in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; they are the chiefeſt, and they haue the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence aboue all other in Gods treaſures.</p>
            <p>After this, the Lord ſpeaketh to the little ones, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>15</label> and ſaith, If thy brother treſpaſſe againſt thee, thou ſhalt tell him his fault, &amp;c. But before I proceed in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19603:38"/>the words of our Lord, which followeth: About the meaning whereof, there is ſo great difference and ſtrife at this day, which hath cauſed great diuiſion and enuie: And becauſe, it being a matter of great moment, and very neceſſary at this day to be known: wee will labour the more diligently (by Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) to diſſolue the doubts, and to bring the truth to light: that by this meanes, the wandring thoughts of thoſe, fled, and diſperſt abroad, might be reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and brought home. And our contentious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits at home alſo, better informed, that we may haue a more ſpirituall, peacefull, and heauenly procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; encreaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good beginnings to moſt happy ends, the which I make no doubt of: if they will but vouchſafe to learne at the hands of trueth. To this end,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.17.18. <hi>verſe of the laſt Chapter.</hi>
               </note> we will firſt ſee what S. <hi>Iohn</hi> meaneth, and then come to our Lords words.</p>
            <p>If any man ſee his brother ſinne a ſinne that is not vnto death, let him aske, and he ſhall giue him life for them that ſinne not vnto death. There is a ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death: I ſay not that ye ſhould pray for it; All vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe is ſinne: but there is a ſinne not vnto death. We know, that whoſoeuer is borne of God, ſinneth not, but he that is begotten of God, keepeth himſelfe, and that wicked one toucheth him not.</p>
            <p>As if hee ſhould ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>16</label> If any man that is borne of God, ſee any one of theſe brethren, that are not yet borne againe, ſinne againſt the light, or thoſe that walke in the light: (ſo it be not in that depth as that it reacheth vnto death,) let him that is born of God, knowing it, aske of God, and he will giue him life for them that ſin not to death.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19603:38"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> There is a ſin vnto death, that ſome of thoſe that are vnborne of God doe commit, not to bee prayed for, that is, a ſinne ſo malitiouſly committed, and with knowledge againſt the light, and with ſo bitter and enuious a ſpirit againſt thoſe alſo that walke in it, that he could withall his heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.5 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.12.</note> ſerue him as <hi>Caine</hi> did his brother: becauſe his owne workes are euill, and his brothers good. And this ſinne is not to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and may bee diſcerned by them which are borne of God, from the other: or elſe how could they tell for whome they ought to pray, and for whome not.</p>
            <p>All vnrighteouſnes is ſinne, and all ſinne is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder the name of vnrighteouſneſſe: ſome of which,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.8</note> all thoſe that are borne of God are guilty of dayly: and ſhall be ſo long as they liue,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.2</note> in this earthly Tabernacle, for which they ſigh and mourne, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for this deliuerance. But there is a ſinne not vnto death: which none of theſe that are borne of God do commit: as he affirmeth in the next words.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> We know (faith he) whoſoeuer is borne of God ſinneth not, that is ſinneth not neither that ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, nor yet the ſinne not vnto death, before mentioned, but he that is begotten of God, keepeth himſelfe, and that wicked one toucheth him not that is through the ſpirit of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22.</note> that ſealeth that holy ſeede, the word of faith to his heart: whereby hee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer commeth the world, and that wicked ſpirit can take no place in him.</p>
            <p>Now let vs returne to the wordes and mind of our Sauiour: now that we perceiue the meaning of his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19603:39"/>ſeruant <hi>Iohn,</hi> being all one and the ſame caſe, and ſee what our Lord doth meane, proceeding where wee left.</p>
            <p>Moreouer if thy brother treſpas againſt thee, thou ſhalt tell him his fault betweene thee and him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Lord hauing from the beginning of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond verſe, of this Chapter, to the end of the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth verſe of the ſame: applyed his ſpeeches,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to thoſe vnregenerate Diſciples and brethren: giuing them to vnderſtand how neceſſary it is that they ſhould conuert: and that to the conuerted little ones, the great things doe belong: and to receiue one of them in his name, is to receiue him: charging them with great threatnings, to take heed that they offend not one of thoſe little ones, ſhewing them how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recouerable a ſinne it is: he pronounceth a woe vpon the committers thereof: And that as a man caſt into the ſea, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſe </seg>7</label> with a mil-ſtone about his necke, cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly returne againe, ſo and more vnpoſſible it is for any one to returne, that falles into this gulfe: And telling them alſo, what great priuiledges they had, how their Meſſengers haue acceſſe into the preſence of his father, and beholde his face in heauen: and how that his wil is, that not one of theſe little ones ſhould periſh.</p>
            <p>I ſay the Lord hauing aduiſed and charged the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>returned ones thus, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſe. </seg>15</label> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.10.</note>doth now turne his ſpeech vnto the little ones borne of God, in whome is no occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euill (as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith) ſhewing them how they ought to walke toward thoſe vnreturned bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19603:39"/>If thy brother treſpas againſt thee, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here we muſt conſider, before we proceed any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what treſpaſſes theſe are, and to this ende let vs looke backe to that which hath beene ſaid from Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> words: As there is a ſinne vnto death,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.16.</note> not to be prayed for, nor yet to be admoniſht of being knowne (for that man, which they know they may not pray for, they doe as well know it is in vaine to admoniſh:) So there is a finne not vnto death, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſe </seg>17</label> which when they ſee any of the vnreturned brethren commit, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the light, or againſt any of them, for the light and Goſpells ſake: that may be both prayed for, and they admoniſht of by them (as it is written) bleſſe them that curſe you, pray for them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 6.28.</note> which perſecute you: as for him that ſinneth wittingly, and willingly againſt the light, and the obeyers therof for the light and Goſpels ſake, after he hath knowne the truth of the ſame:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26.</note> there doth remaine no more ſacrifice of ſinne, &amp;c. Of whome one ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.5</note> praying againſt the wicked. Bee not mercifull to them that tranſgreſſe maliciouſly:</p>
            <p>So to him that ſinneth, or treſpaſſeth, vnwitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly though willingly againſt the light, and them that walke in it, as many often doe reuile and perſecute them, thinking they doe God ſeruice: There doth yet remaine ſacrifice, and he may be both prayed for,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 16.2</note> and exhorted to repentance, and repenting find grace and pardon, both with God and his true Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.34 <hi>Act.</hi> 7.60</note> and for ſuch doth the Lord himſelfe pray, (ſaying) Father forgiue them, for they know not what they doe, and another ſaith, Lord lay not this ſinne to their charge.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19603:40"/>So that this ſinne or treſpaſſe heere, is not any ſinne committed ſimply and alone, againſt the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements: But it is to ſinne againſt the new co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant in them that obey it: For the Lord doth not heere giue rules, and directions whereby to learne men to keepe the ten commaundements, but to teach them to obey the Goſpell; yet not ſo, but that euery ſinne committed againſt the Goſpell, is alſo a breach of the law; But one may ſinne againſt the law and yet not againſt the Goſpell, not that any man hath leaue to ſinne againſt, or breake any of the ten commandements, but in many things, (as one ſaith) we ſinne all, and loue couereth a multitude of theſe ſinnes, and as it is written,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.2. 1. <hi>Pet</hi> 4.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1</note> Bleſſed is that man whoſe iniquities are couered, ſo that as God in his loue doth couer the manifold iniquities of his bleſſed ones, ſo doe they all couer multitudes of thoſe ſinnes in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>And that it cannot bee meant of the literall breach of any of the ten commaundements, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may proue; for if a man ſee his brother commit adultery, or murder, or theft, or heare him take the name of God invaine, or ſee him worſhip an Idoll, or any other ſuch like groſſe ſinne, how may theſe rules and directions, in this place, ſerue for this man, for after that he, which onely is priuie to his fault (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide God and himſelfe) hath plainely rebuked him: as the Scripture other where doth commande him ſo to doe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.17.</note> If hee will nor heare him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> how may he then proceed according to the direction of Chriſt if he take one or two, and then telleth him his fault,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19603:40"/>and reproue him before them or him, and the other denieth any ſuch fault that he accuſeth him of, and taketh him or them, whom he bringeth for witneſſe, to beare witneſſe againſt him, to proue him a ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, and ſo he may proceede againſt him (in mens iudgement) more lawfully, and more agreeable to Chriſts direction, then he may againſt the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath one or two witneſſes, whereas the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath none: and ſo thoſe witneſſes, whom he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to beare witnes againſt another, commeth now againſt himſelfe: wherefore it is manifeſt, that no man may accuſe another of any ſinne (eſpecially of that kind) though he ſaw it with his eyes, or heard it with his eares, except he hath other eye or eare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes beſides himſelfe, leaſt hee bee condemned for tranſgreſsion, and puniſhed for an euill doer:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.15.</note> for an accuſation may not be receiued vnder two or three witneſſes.</p>
            <p>So then the Lord dooth not meane here, by treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, any of the groſſe ſinnes of the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor yet the ſmaller multitudes of them, which loue doth couer, but hee meaneth the ſinnes or treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes committed againſt the little ones, that are borne againe, hating them or deſpiſing them, for that they walke in the light, and ſo in deſpiſing them they deſpiſe the Lord Ieſus, and his father that ſent him, and ſo they ſin againſt that light which ſhould ſaue their ſoules; which being done wittingly, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable. And as the law of life and ſaluation is more excellent then the law of death, ſo doth the ſin excell in greatneſſe: (As it is written) If he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19603:41"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28, 29.</note>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> law, died without mercie, vnder two or three witneſſes, O how much ſorer puniſhment ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ye ſhall he be worthy, that treadeth vnder feete the Sonne of God, and counteth the blood of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament as an vnholy thing, wherewith hee was ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and doth deſpight the ſpirit of grace! So then to ſinne againſt the law is one thing, and to ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Goſpell is another: Wherefore by treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe here is meant pardonable ſinne, committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the new Teſtament; and thoſe that walke in the light thereof vnwittingly. And the treſpaſſers, are ſuch as are not yet borne of God: for hee that is borne of God ſinneth not,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.18.</note> neither is there any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euill in him: meaning by ſinne and euill; the ſinne to death, and the ſinne not to death, before mentioned: for if he could ſinne the ſinne not to death, hee muſt needes ſinne the ſinne to death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot doe it ignorantly: As <hi>Paul</hi> did,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</note> who ſaid I was receiued to mercy, for I did it ignorantly, ſeeing he knoweth the light, which <hi>Paul</hi> did not then; for how is it poſſible that he which is borne of God, who loueth God and his brother alſo, that is begotten of him, who walketh in the light (which is his life and ſaluation) that he ſhould hate his brother whom hee ſo loueth, or deſpiſe the light which his ſoule deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in, or reſiſt the ſame, ſeeing that his whole life and felicity doth conſiſt therein? And we know that he that is borne of God, loueth God, and he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth God,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.9.</note> loueth his brother alſo, which is begotten of God; and ſo he cannot ſinne, neither is there any occaſion of thoſe euils in him (as it is written):<note place="margin">1. <hi>John</hi> 5.1.</note> Now
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19603:41"/>let vs proceed, ſeeing that the way (as I hope) is made cleere.</p>
            <p>If thy brother treſpaſſe againſt thee, goe tell him his fault between thee and him alone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15.</note> if he heare thee, thou haſt wonne thy brother: That is to ſay, If any one of thoſe Diſciples and brethren in common things, not regenerate, doe deſpiſe or ſpeake euill of any one of you, that are returned, and reuile or perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you for the lights ſake, wherein you walke: Thou ſhalt informe him of his fault between thee and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone, and giue him to vnderſtand, that if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, ſpeake euill of, reuile, or perſecute thee, he doth it vnto the Lord whom he profeſſeth, &amp; exhort him to humble his heart, and be conuerted, and walke in that light himſelfe: and then hee ſhall loue both it, and embrace and loue them alſo that walke in it: if he take knowledge of his faults, and receiueth thy words of exhortation and counſell, and ſay vnto thee, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth me: thou ſhalt forgiue him, ſeeing thou haſt won thy brother; but if he heare thee not, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>16</label> take yet with thee one or two, that by the mouth of two or three witneſſes, euery word may be confirmed: That is to ſay, if he ſcorne thy information., and deſpiſe both thee and thy exhortation, ſtill proceeding in his euill againſt thee, and the light in thee, thou ſhalt not yet giue him ouer, but take yet with thee one or two of thy fathers owne children, of thoſe little returned ones thy brethren, and ſeeke his loue (as before) with all courteſie and meekeneſſe of exhortation: and if he ſtill reſiſt thy loue, and vtter wordes of ſcorne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, or reuile thee, as enuie cannot hide it ſelfe:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19603:42"/>Then can that one or two, witneſſe againſt him, and will, if that he will not heare them neither, (but firſt let them alſo admoniſh him) that ſo euery word that he ſpeaketh euill againſt thee, or the light in thee, may be confirmed. And if he refuſe to heare them, tell it vnto the Church, &amp; if he refuſe to heare the Church alſo, let him be vnto thee as an Heathen man and a Publican: that is, If hee ſtill like a ſcorner, refuſe to giue eare and to receiue inſtruction, at the handes of that one witneſſe with thee or two, tell it to the Church,<note place="margin">Theſe he hath made Pillars in his houſe, and they ſhall goe no more out. <hi>Reu.</hi> 3.12.</note> that is, to thoſe little ones borne of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gathered together in my name, who onely haue this priuiledge to be my Church and Pillar of truth; for if there were fiue hundred brethren more beſide the little humble ones, yet none can iudge this cauſe but they. This Church doth neuer condemn the ino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and let the guilty goe free. This Church neuer decreed lies, and condemned the truth. And if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to heare this Church, let him bee vnto thee no longer as a brother, and a fellow partaker in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things of the kingdome, wherein before he did and might take part with thee, as a diſciple of Chriſt, but let him be vnto thee, and vnto all the Church, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as a Heathen that beleeueth not the truth of the Ghoſpell, and as a Publican that profeſſeth the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of ſinne: Verily I ſay vnto you, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>18</label> whatſoeuer you binde on earth ſhall be bound in heauen, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in heauen: for to you it is, to whom I haue giuen the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heauen, as well to binde them that ſinne againſt you, and the Conenant of loue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19603:42"/>written in you, with the bond of death, and to ſhut the gate of mercy and loue againſt them, as alſo to loſe the bonds of iniquity, and the cords and chaines of their ſinnes, that do repent: and to open the gates of my kingdome of mercy &amp; life vnto them: ſo that whatſoeuer ye binde on earth, is bound in heauen, and whatſoeuer ye loſe on earth, is loſed in heauen. For if he eſcaped not, that deſpiſed him that ſpake on earth, how ſhould he then eſcape, that deſpiſeth him that ſpeaketh from heauen? And as he died without mercy vnder two or three witneſſes, that deſpiſed <hi>Moyſes</hi> law: Much more lamentable, and fearefull, is the condition of him, that deſpiſeth that law, and couenant of grace, whereby his ſoule ſhould liue: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the voice of the bride, and of her children, which ſought his good. How much greater is his bondage, and ſorer ſhall his puniſhment be, that is condemned by that Church, (where the Prince of the couenant doth ſit) of treaſon againſt his bloud, by the teſtimony of two or three witneſſes, It had been good for that man if he neuer had beene borne. And better for him, after hee was borne, that a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone had beene hanged about his neck, and throwne to the bottome of the Sea, before he fell to deſpiſe the Lord in his Sanctuarie, and to reſiſt his ſpirit of grace in his little ones.</p>
            <p>Againe, verily I ſay vnto you, That if two of you my brethren, that beleene in me, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>19</label> agree in earth vpon any thing concerning my word, and the meaning thereof, either for the ſentence of death to the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, or mercy and life to the returned ſinner,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19603:43"/>whatſoeuer ye ſhall aske the Father in my name (if it be life, for him that ſinneth not vnto death, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe is neceſſary and good for the kingdome) he will giue it you.</p>
            <p>For, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>20</label> where two or three be gathered in my name, there am I in the middeſt of you, what will hee not therefore giue you for my ſake, Aske and ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that your ioy may be full. Theſe are priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, belonging only to thoſe little ones that are born of God, who haue their parts in the firſt reſurrection, againſt whom the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile, nor yet the ſecond death.</p>
            <p>But there was euermore an <hi>Iſraell</hi> after the fleſh, which perſecuted that <hi>Iſraell</hi> which is after the ſpirit, and ſhall be to the worlds end. For this generation ſhal not paſſe away till the Lord himſelfe come.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.34.</note> And if there were not an <hi>Iſraell</hi> not of God, <hi>Paul</hi> would neuer haue ſaid. (To the <hi>Iſraell</hi> which is of God) And if there were not an earthly Ieruſalem, he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue told vs of a heauenly.</p>
            <p>Yea, there were two Ieruſalems in all times: Two Iſraels in all ages, two mothers, two teſt aments, two ſeeds, euen from the beginning: As <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abell, Iſmaell</hi> and <hi>Iſaack, Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob:</hi> Two lands of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, heauenly and earthly: Two reſts, carnall and ſpirituall, As it is written, ſaying: To day if ye will heare his voice, harden not your hearts, leaſt ye enter not into this reſt: Euen then while they were in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the earthly reſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.15.16.17.18.19.</note> which by vnhardning their hearts, and hearing his voice, they might haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into. Euen the ſame way which euer was, ſtill
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19603:43"/>remaines, and ſhall doe to the worlds end. Euen the ſame reſt, the ſame heauenly Ieruſalem, the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the firſt borne, the ſame holy City, the ſame Church, which hath had in it at all times, the ſame power from God to binde and looſe, to remit and to retain ſinnes, And this is the bride, the Lambs wife, This is ſhe, to whom is granted to be cloathed in white aray: And theſe are they that watch, and are ſober, attending with their Lampes burning, to meete the bridgeroome their husband. Theſe all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardened their hearts, and heard his voice, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into his reſt. The reſt and peace with God, reſt to their ſoules, euen that reſt which is ſaid to remain to the people of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9.</note> And whoſoeuer entred into that reſt, did firſt heare his voice, that is, receiued the word of faith. And whoſoeuer receiued that word of faith; did firſt vnharden his heart: that is, did firſt repent: was loſt, and dead, crying, and bewailing, with an vn-vtterable deſire of life, his ſinnes &amp; death. and theſe are the dead which heare the voice of the ſonne of man, and liue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.25.</note> And this is that one baptiſme ſpoken of, and is called the baptiſme of repentance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 19.4. <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.1.2.3.4</note> and the beginning of the Goſpell, the preparation to the word of faith. (That one faith ſpoken of,) and they that are borne againe of theſe two,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.5.</note> haue all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that one ſpirit ſpoken of, euen the ſpirit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, and are all ſeruants vnto that one Lord, and children to that one God their Father, who is aboue all, and through all, and in them all. And theſe are entred into the kingdome of heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</note> which is not meate, and drinke, and apparrell: but righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19603:44"/>and peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Now let vs ſpeake a little of the liberty and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this kingdome. This kingdome is free, not in bondage, but at liberty, whereſoeuer ſhe liueth in any kingdome or common-wealth, and if the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie thereof, ſay eate, they eate: or drinke, they drinke: or put on, they put on: obſerue and keepe, touch, or taſt, or handle, or pay, they obey: If they forbid, they alſo heare, and forbeare; both in theſe and all other things of the like nature. And ſo are they obedient to all manner ordinances of man, for the Lords ſake; againſt whoſe commandement elſe they ſhould ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.25.</note> who ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7.</note> Giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> thoſe things that are <hi>Caeſars.</hi> And there is no kingdome, or ſtate whatſoeuer, where Chriſtians are not in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage (if it bee a bondage) to ſome of theſe. And if there were (which is vnpoſſible) then were it left to their choiſe, to take or leaue with moderation, as pleaſe them: as it is alſo vnder a gouernment, where many things of the ſame nature are ſo left, neither commanded, nor forbidden And herein conſiſteth their liberty, in that it toucheth not their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, For whether they eate, or eate not, they ſinne not, for God requireth neither the one nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherfore if we giue theſe things to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> we do wrong neither to God, nor yet to our conſciences, but rather if we giue not, being required: as the Lord himſelfe ſaid in the like caſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.27.</note> Pay it to them leaſt wee offend.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Caeſar</hi> muſt haue, and be obeyed in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer belongs to him, ſo wee muſt giue vnto God
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19603:44"/>whatſoeuer he requires, and obey him in whatſoeuer he commands. Now the greateſt difficulty lieth in this, to diſtinguiſh betweene the things of God, and the things of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that knowing them aſunder, we may the better know how, &amp; wherein, to obey both God and <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein, by the grace of my God, I will not ſay any thing for any reſpect, in and of the world whatſoeuer, but Gods truth and his Church: ſeeing that I know, it ſhal come to the tryal of ſuch a touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone which cannot erre: Who will waigh it, try it, and condemne it, if it be found corrupt, or too light, And although it be a common fault in men, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the preſent and generall affection: and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the moſt and greateſt, ſway they as they will: Yet inſomuch as I know, that God is in all times and ſeeth in al places, be they neuer ſo ſecret, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that he hath eyes abroad that can ſee, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be blind, and lyes goe as current as truth with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and ſeeing I know, not onely this time, but a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time ſhall try it, I will therefore bee aduiſed and take heede what I ſay, for aſſuredly, there is no lye, made by the cunningſt inuenter of lyes whatſoeuer, but ſhall once, eyther ſooner or later, ſuffer death at the hands of truth. And there is no ſtubble or ſtraw whatſoeuer, but ſhall bee conſumed with the flame thereof.</p>
            <p>Now let vs ſee, firſt what are the things of God, which doth belong to him: And then we ſhall the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier ſee, what are <hi>Caeſars</hi> thinges that belong to him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.23.34.</note> The things of God are truth and ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 17.17.</note> his truth is his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19603:45"/>word, his worde is his law: his law is of two ſorts, and therefore is called two Teſtaments.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.23.24. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 17.17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> The Teſtament and law of death: and the Reuelation and Couenant of life.</p>
            <p>All the Scriptures are true, but all that is written therein is not the word of God: For ſometimes the holy Ghoſt ſets downe the ſinnes and practiſes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill men:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 28.</note> And ſometimes he deſcribeth vnto vs the lying wordes of the falſe prophets: which when wee read, we muſt not take it for the word of God, but that it is true, we muſt beleeue: for they which wrote it could not erre therein, and therefore truth it is, but not the truth.</p>
            <p>The word of God then, and the truth we meane, Is that which came from heauen, whether that iuſt and holy law of commaundements, which is called the miniſter of death, becauſe we could not fulfill it, and therfore it could not giue vs life, but the iuſt ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death; or that perfect law and teſtament of life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7.</note> which conuerteth ſoules, I meane the Goſpell, which is in a more ſpeciall and peculiar maner, called the word of God, then the law is or can be, as where it ſaith, Faith commeth by hearing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</note> and hearing by the worde of God. And againe we haue a moſt ſure worde of the Prophets, vnto the which ye doe well that yee giue heed, &amp;c. And in diuers other places both in the new and old Teſtament, whereby, nothing is meant (by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meanes) but the promiſe and word of life: And therefore he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.17.</note> Sanctifie them through thy word: thy word is the truth. Now, in theſe two Teſtaments is declared whatſoeuer God requireth: eyther due to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19603:45"/>himſelfe from vs, whether it be faith or obedience: And alſo our duetie to our neighbours, of all ſorts, high and low, good and bad, and all the holy Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, &amp; Reuelations which came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue: and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſhadows whatſoeuer, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſcriptures do ſet forth vnto vs: do tend to one or other of theſe two? and both and all, doe tend eyther to ſhew forth the riches of God, in his bounty and mercy, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of thoſe that turne, obey his Goſpell, and loue his law: or his ſeuerity and iuſtice, in the condition of thoſe that diſobey both lawe and Goſpell. That the end of all might bee the glory of God, and of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now the ſpeciall things of God, that doe belong peculiarly to him alone, are they that we muſt ſpeake of. His peculiar things are theſe, firſt as from him we are gone aſtray, and by his holy law pronounced dead: ſo to him alone we muſt returne to ſeeke life: for he alone can giue it vs, In him alone we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and put our confidence: to him alone wee muſt pray, and hee onely muſt be our God, and chiefe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light Him onely we muſt feare as God: him only we muſt loue as God: him onely wee muſt acknowledge for our Sauiour, and Redeemer: his commandements muſt be obeyed onely aboue all: and hee onely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with our whole ſpirits. For he alone muſt haue our hearts, and this is ſpirit ioyned with truth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 4.21.</note> Neither this mountaine nor that, doth hee require, nor yet forbid: what he commaundeth not, <hi>Ceſar</hi> may forbid, what he forbiddeth not, <hi>Ceſar</hi> may command. God requireth euery place alike: <hi>Ceſar</hi> may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19603:46"/>a place for the publike ſo he doe forbid none in priuate. God requireth not apparrell: <hi>Ceſar</hi> may forbid: God forbiddeth not: <hi>Ceſar</hi> may commaund. Where there is no law, there is libertie, wee were in bondage once (indeede) when ſhaddowes were in place, but now we are freed and ſet at liberty, by the Son who is free, and the very ſubſtance is in him.</p>
            <p>God commaundeth all times for prayers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Ceſar</hi> one time, forbidding no time, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no law; for euery (one, is contained in all: And ſo in all other things, that are not eyther commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or forbidden of God: and in obeying <hi>Ceſar</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, wee giue vnto <hi>Ceſar</hi> the thinges that are <hi>Ceſars,</hi> whereas otherwiſe, if we obey him not, wee are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the breach of the morall law, which ſaieth, Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe. And ſo breaking this one great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, we are guilty of that other, the greateſt of all. Thou ſhalt loue thy Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule; &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For although God doth not appoint and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund <hi>Ceſar,</hi> in all, what lawes hee ſhall make: yet doth hee confirme all thoſe lawes which hee doth made: which are not contrary to his owne lawes, and commandeth obedience thereto at the handes of all ſubiects to their Kings and gouernours, and all other their ſuperiours, bee they good or bad, of what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſoeuer he be, whether Prophet, or Prieſt, or Biſhop true of falſe: ſo he haue power, he muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed: or elſe we are guilty of the wole law of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1</note> for all the powers that be (as one ſaith) are ordayned
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19603:46"/>of God. And therefore whoſoeuer hee be that lyeth in priſon, or ſuffereth any puniſhment (whatſoeuer) for diſobeying of any of theſe his gouernours, in any of thoſe lawes or Canons not oppoſite to Gods lawes, he ſuffereth as an euill doer, and ſo depriueth himſelfe of that liberty, which the Apoſtle exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to, ſaying. Stand faſt in the liberty wherin Chriſt had made you free, and be not entangled againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1.</note> &amp;c. If you doe well ſaith one, who will harme you.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.</note> The daes are paſt long a goe wherein there was a law which ſaid, Touch not, taſt not, handle not, &amp;c. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with conſciences might be defiled, but thanks bee to God, who hath freed vs through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, that whether wee eate or eate not, tough or touch not, obſerue or obſerue not, wee offend not, ſo that wee haue knowledge, neither God nor our conſciences, ſo that withall we take heede and make not this liberty a cloake for ſinne. It is a good gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for a Saint, but not for a ſinner, for hee takes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty there-vnder,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 6</note> to runne into all kind of riot and exceſſe, But we, as we muſt giue vnto <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Ceſars:</hi> So wee muſt giue vnto God the things that are Gods: And in thoſe things which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God nor <hi>Ceſar</hi> doth require, but is in our owne liberty to take our leaue, as to eate and drinke, to put on, to buy, and the like: heerein wee muſt not exceed, leaſt it ouercome and rule our affections, and ſo wee turne our liberty to ſin, much rather let vs forbeare, finding them not expedient, for though all thinges are lawfull (as one ſaith) yet all things are not expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.12.</note> I will not be brought ſaith hee vnder the power
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19603:47"/>of any thing. And looke on the (ſaith he in another place) who walke ſo as ye haue vs for an example,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.17.18.19.20.</note> for many walke, of whome I haue told you often, and now tell you weeping, who are enemies to the Creſſe of Chriſt, whoſe end is da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, whoſe God their belly, and glory to their ſhame, which minde earthly things, but our conuerſation is in he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>auen. And therefore let vs giue vnto God the things that are Gods, and to <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Ceſars.</hi> And if <hi>Ceſar</hi> ſhould require any thing which belongeth to God, let vs giue him our liues, if we had ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, before hee ſhould haue it,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17.</note> and then we ſhould not ſuffer as euill doers, but for righteouſneſſe ſake.</p>
            <p>Theſe things look vnto, you that run from coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to country, and you alſo that ſtay at home, and trouble the proceedings of Sion. Know this that yee ſuffer as euill doers, and cauſe others alſo to doe the like, by following your ſteppes.</p>
            <p>But ſome man perhaps will ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> I could almoſt finde in my heart to obey <hi>Ceſar</hi> the King, but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide theſe Prelates the Biſhops to obey them (canſt thou not indeed?) Take loue into thy breaſt, and then thou ſhalt ſee what thou canſt doe. I but thou wilt ſay, Hee is no <hi>Ceſar,</hi> not yet a lawfull go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, his calling and power is Antichriſtian, and it came from the beaſt, The Pope of Rome, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not his power from God, but from the great red Dragon the diuell.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> Well, I aunſwere: Heere thou art deceiued two wayes, firſt whereas thou ſaieſt, that our Biſhops re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their callings &amp; power from the beaſt the Pope
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19603:47"/>of Rome, is vntrue: In former times indeede they did; but now they receiue their callings and power from <hi>Caeſar</hi> our King, who hath authority to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and appoint,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Titus</hi> 3.1.</note> euery publique calling in all his kingdomes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.14.</note> tending to the common-wealth of all his ſubiects, as well for the feeding of their ſoules, as for the preſeruation of their bodies and goods. And this is a charge laide vpon him by God himſelfe, as euery houſholder is bound to prouide (to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer) all things neceſſary for his houſhold, both for ſoule and body: And as the King is bound to ſee all his great houſhold prouided for (to his power) and to place ouer them the beſt and fitteſt for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I mean for ſoule and body: So he may giue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authority to all ſorts of them, to performe the will of God, and to ſee his owne lawes kept and executed, without reſiſtance or diſturbance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whereas thou ſaieſt, that the beaſt, the Pope, receiued his power from the great red Dragon the diuell: Thou ſaiſt true, but thou ſhalt ſee, if thou wilt looke well vpon the matter, how thou doeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thy ſelfe, For tell mee, who was that great red Dragon? was it the diuell himſelfe alone, or was it the Emperour in whom the diuell dwelt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.3.</note> who is ſaid to haue ſeuen heads and ten hornes? wherewith the diuell alone is neuer deſcribed, but the Emperour it was that gaue him his power, and his Throane, and great authority, in whom the diuell dwelt, as he doth in all ſuch like bloudy Tyrants: And as he hath done in the beaſt the Dragons ſucceſſour, (in more cruell malice and deceit) aboue forty of his two and forty
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19603:48"/>moneths:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ren.</hi> 13.5.</note> wherein power was giuen him to doe.</p>
            <p>But tell me, who gaue the Emperour his power? was it not God, Chriſt our Lord ſaith to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Deputy <hi>Pilat:</hi> Thou couldſt haue no power (ſaith he) except it were giuen thee from aboue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.10.</note> So then whether it be the Emperours Deputy <hi>Pilat:</hi> or his ſucceſſour, the Pope: or any other that hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and power: Their power is giuen them from aboue, whatſoeuer they be. And ſo one ſaith true, All powers that be,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> are ordained of God, and he that reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God: So that what power ſo euer it be, and in whatſoeuer they command or forbid: They muſt be obeyed; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes prouided, that they command not that which God forbiddeth, or forbid that which God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. And ſo wee giue to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe things are loathſome in your eares, and eyes, and this (of all other) vvill goe hardeſt downe with you. For the power and authority of Biſhops, you hold, is Antichriſtian, and to obey their lawes and ordinances, you ſay, is to worſhip the beaſt: Though the things they commaund be neuer ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently lawfull in themſelues, to be done or left vndone, their authority and commaund (you ſay) makes it abhominable.</p>
            <p>And this is not your ſaying alone: it is a ſore that hath feſtered theſe thirty yeares in England, and hath bred diuers Sects and infectiue errors: Our Teachers and writers for pretended reformation, were the firſt planters thereof, who through their ignorance (in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19603:48"/>their heat) not diſcerning betweene the thinges of God, and the things of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for want of knowledge concerning Chriſtian liberty, conceiued a law of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding, and gaue it out, charging the people vppon paine of condemnation to be obedient thereunto: whereby they haue brought themſelues and many hundred poore ſoules beſides, (loaden with ſinne) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a further captiuity and greater bondage then they were in before: For whereas their ſinnes onely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt them, and remembring Gods promiſe, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt eſcaped: This law of their Teachers came ſo ſuddenly on the necke of them, that they were driuen into a harder ſtreight, and vnder a more vnrecouera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burden then they were before: which hath beene ſo weariſome vnto them, that to eaſe themſelues, they haue made Sects, and running into them, haue fallen into many groſſe errours: ſome alſo falling to, and embracing this preſent world: Onely a remnant God hath, and will deliuer from theſe wayward and diſtaſtful ſpirits, and giue them to ſee, how Chriſtians are free, and yet ſubiects to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and how the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is no more defiled by the commaunder (of what condition ſoeuer hee bee) in their obedience, then it ſhould be by leauing it vndone, if neyther man nor God require it: for as wee are freed from the law of Ceremonies (once in force before the death of Chriſt) that there is now no more conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be made of them: but as to be circumciſed is nothing ſo to be vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed is nothing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.1, 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3.</note> as we may ſee by the example of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> who after the death, reſurrection, and aſcenſion of Ieſus Chriſt,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19603:49"/>and the holy Ghoſt was ſent vnto the Church: after which time Circumciſion was as abſolutely aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with all the whole law of Ceremonies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 21.24, 25, 26.</note> as euer it was ſince to this day: yet <hi>Paul</hi> did purifie himſelfe after the maner of the Iewes, and circumciſed <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy:</hi> To proue and ſhew vnto vs, euen to the worlds end, That there is no more holineſſe or Religion, in making conſcience to abſtaine from Circumciſion, then there is to be Circumciſed: for as it is nothing now to be Circumciſed (ſeeing the end of it was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh't long agoe) ſo is it nothing to bee vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.18, 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So that if a man of God ſhould now be circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to the like end as <hi>Timothy</hi> was, or ſhould faſhion himſelfe like a Iew,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4, 5, 6.</note> to the ſame end that <hi>Paul</hi> did, he ſhould ſinne no more then <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> did. Neither ſhould a man offend, if he ſhould ſit at Table in the Idols Temple, and eate of the meate ſacrificed to an Idoll, ſo that he know that an Idoll is nothing in the world, and dooth eſteeme it as the duſt vnder his feete, he ſinneth not: ſo that hee bow not, nor giue or ſhew any reuerence,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23, 28, 29.</note> either to the Idoll, the Temple, or the Feaſt, but onely receiue the meate with giuing thankes to God: Alwaies prouided too withall, that there be no weake brother that dooth make conſcience for want of knowledge, which is offended thereat, nor yet any Chriſtian (as then there were ſome) that hauing beene bred and brought vp, among Idolaters, and long accuſtomed to the Idoll ſeruice, did yet thinke that there was ſome conſcience to bo made,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 7.</note> &amp; ieuerence to be had of it, that might be
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19603:49"/>emboldened thereby in that their ſinne, or encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereby, to fall to worſhip the Idoll againe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.</note> and to doe ſeruice vnto it. I ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 10.</note> all theſe thinges being conſidered, and conſcionably regarded, and preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: It is no ſinne to ſit at Table in the Idols Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to eate the meate ſacrificed to Idols: But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe all theſe things conſidered, and done, (as is aforeſaid) If he eate meat ſacrificed to Idols, or ſit at the Idols Table, he ſinneth againſt the brethren, and ſo againſt God; and not onely ſo but if he yeeld any reuerence, he is alſo an Idolater,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23.7.</note> and ſinneth againſt God in a more high degree.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe thinges may bee lawfully done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Idolaters, and in their Temples, as then Chriſtians liued for the moſt part amongſt Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: and as theſe Scriptures doe euidently proue was in their liberty: and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, To the Iew I become as a Iew, that I may winne the Iew;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19.20.21.22.23.</note> to the Graecian, and the Graecian, &amp;c. Yea, I am made all things to all men, to the end that I might win ſome. And alſo that of the Aſſirian, when hee ſhould goe into the houſe of the Idoll <hi>Rimmon,</hi> and bow downe for his Maſter to leane on,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 5.18.19.</note> when he was worſhipping to the Idoll: when he made doubt of it, the Prophet bad him goe in peace. I ſay if theſe things bee thus farre in our liberty among the heathen, and in place of Idolatry, where the end and intent is abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: And alſo among the Iewes concerning the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, whoſe end is abſolutely aboliſhed: As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in Rome, whoſe commaundements of all other haue in them the greateſt abhomination: ſo that we
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19603:50"/>partake not with them in their ſinnes, leaſt we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of their plagues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 18.4.</note> If wee may among all theſe, yeeld and obey, in things indifferent, whatſoeuer the commander be, as thoſe Scriptures before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned doth witneſſe: How much more ought wee to be obedient to the lawes and ordinances of England, ſeeing they intend not, neither Idolatry nor ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. Conſidering alſo what great difference there is betweene our Commanders (in profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) and the commanders of the heathen, and of Rome, the City of abhominations. For if I ſhould aske you, what King with his vnder gouernours, is there is the world, that doth command the truth of Religion, in generall, like the King and Gouernours of England: And you are reformers that ſtand ſo much vpon termes? What law is there in England impoſed vpon you contrary to Gods law? Conſider and tell vs. I know what you haue pretended a great while, and we haue ſeene the iſſue of it: but looke a little better vpon the matter, and ſearch throughly. If you finde any contrary to God, and his law impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon you (but looke ye be in a ſure ground) Obey them not, what King ſoeuer command you, let him firſt haue all, euen your liues: If not, take heed, ſuffer not like euill doers, as you haue done a great while: and as you haue pretended reformation in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, now reforme your ſelues in particular: for be it knowne vnto you, your doctrines, and proceedings, haue beene the cauſe of much euill, you haue beene the breeders of theſe ſects, you haue laid the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and others build.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:19603:50"/>
            <p> Their buildings ſtand vpon your foundation, and therefore you are no more able to deale with them in this controuerſie, then one is able to deale with his enemie, when hee hath yeelded him all his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons: For by the ſame reaſon that you inuay againſt the ceremonies (as ye call them) will they come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you for going to the aſſemblies in the Temple: and as you find fault with them for want of an elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the ordination of their paſtors: They defend their proceedings by the ſame reaſons, that you deny the Authority of your Presbitery at home. And you would alſo haue the Church of the ſame faſhion as they: For you agree with them that non ought to be baptiſed, but ſuch as doe firſt ſhew forth vnto you the fruits of regeneration: Whereupon dependeth their Separation and Rebaptiſings, and then ought not children to bee baptiſed, for they ſhew forth no fruits of Regeneration: ſo that if al be true which you ſay, that is true which they doe, and ſo you are the ſayers, and they the doers, And therefore you muſt of neceſſity, either ioyne with them, or change your minds, or elſe hide your ſelues for ſhame; for ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fight with them, ſeeing you are vnarmed, &amp; they haue all your weapons. Therefore as you haue troubled many a poore ſoule with your doubtfull Doctrines, vnder pretence of abſtaining from ſinne, and performing of holy duties, that many of you, and of your followers, differ but little from the Sect of the Phariſes: So now at laſt, ſee if yee can learne to giue them better inſtruction.</p>
            <p>And as you haue beene the Authors of Sects,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19603:51"/>and many errors, which hath bred much diſtraction, and trouble of ſpirit, as is to be ſeene this day both at home and abroad, now at laſt ſeeke to redreſſe it, for it is lamentable to behold, how many hundreds of people, (no doubt ſingle and vpright in heart, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring and thirſting for peace and reſt to their ſoules) haue beene by you ſeduced and brought into a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bondage: And alſo throught their deuotion and bounty vnto you, haue brought themſelues (ſome of them) into great wants, and miſeries: ſome with feaſting of you, ſome with l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, ſome with giuing: and ſome to eaſe their conciences, which you had burdened, and to eſcape trouble, haue left their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, remooued their dwellings; ſolde their poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fled their countrey, ſeparating themſelues from the Church of England as from Idolatry, and the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations of Antichriſt. And beeing beyond the ſeas (In Holland by name) beholding among the Sects of Separatiſts there, The wranglings, the braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, the deuiſions, the enuie, and the groſſe ſins that hath beene amongſt them, haue been driuen to their witts ends, running from Sect to Sect, and from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to error, that ſome of them now at laſt, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come carnall and blaſphemous Familiſts: betweene whom and the worldlings, there is little difference, but onely in their doctrines and blaſphemies. Others (the better of the two) Imbracing meerely this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world. Onely a few haue eſcaped, whome God hath better inſtructed, who can tell how, through his grace, to giue vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and vnto God the things that are God.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:19603:51"/>
            <p> And now yet for all this, neither you nor your followers, haue once called into queſtion, your begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and grounds of theſe things: but they are ſo blinded with you, and you with your long accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med errors, (your ſuppoſed truth) and with the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments you haue ſo long maintained, againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops their titles, their places, and callings, The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions and ceremonies as ye call them: that you haue ſtill proceeded, in your blind zeale: euen to ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and impriſoning: and they on the other ſide, in their deuotion and ſimple zeale of your Doctrine and you, ſo that they haue miniſtred ſo bountifully vnto you, and that out of their penury ſome of them, that you haue filled your bagges with money, and your bellies with cheere, (ſome of you) when ſome of your poore contributors, and followers, haue ſit with many a hungry meale at home, with many a ſigh and trouble in ſpirit, when as neither you, nor your rich followers, haue ſcarce euer enquired, or lookt after them. And you are ſo cunning ſome of you, that you can plead pouerty to increaſe your ſtore, that you may haue hundreds to ſpare againſt anotherday. And herein your greateſt and richeſt followers are ſo partial, they wil giue you a pound, and plenty offeaſts &amp; cheere: when they wil hardly giue their poore hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry brother a penny, a cup of cold water, or a piece of bread: And this they haue learned of you, who are alſo as partiall as they, if not more: for they that fill you with delicates, and that put pounds into your purſes, you will viſite, and that often: you are well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with their dores, whereas though there bee
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19603:52"/>ten poore to one rich, of all your followers, yet you know not the way to their dores, nor the place where they dwell: they are ſtrangers, and vnknowne except they viſit you: Are not theſe your procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings? I know what I ſay, it is pitifull to ſee, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your poore followers, are in great and extreme wants with their wiues and children: Looke vnto it therefore, and repent: for be it knowne vnto you, God will raiſe them out of the duſt (that you thinke not) who ſhall Ecclips your light, <hi>Iacob</hi> is diſquieted by your meanes, and Iſrael by you cauſed to erre.</p>
            <p>And for you Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> and your company: here is newes come to England already, that you are deuided: and you know what muſt come to a deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded kingdome, &amp; a houſe againſt it ſelfe. That which cannot ſtand, muſt fall: and that which cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, ſhall come to nought. Seeke ſtrength of the Lord, and requeſt that you may ſtand in his Courts, and dwell in his houſe, whoſe pillars endure for euer.</p>
            <p>But perhaps ſome will ſay; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> If we ſhould yeeld and obey as you ſay, how ſhould we then ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and be afflicted? how ſhould we be hated of all Nations (as Chriſt ſaith) for his name ſake? Leaue theſe differences and controuerſies, and leaue all. Then let vs take our pleaſure, and ſhake hands with the world, and looke after preferments in the earth, and promotions as others doe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> Vnwiſe man, whatſoeuer thou at that doeſt make this obiection, and doeſt ſo ſpeake. For tell me, muſt thou needs erre on the right hand or on the left. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19603:52"/>the law of our land doth not perſecute thee for righteouſneſſe ſake? wilt thou therefore be diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and ſuffer for thy ſinnes? Becauſe a godly life and perſecution cannot be ſeperated in this world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, as it is written,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12.</note> Whoſoeuer will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus, muſt ſuffer perſecution: and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer will be his Diſciple, muſt take vp his croſſe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and follow him, wilt thou therefore (becauſe thou knoweſt not how to take vp his Croſſe, nor how to liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus) Take vp a Croſſe of thine owne making,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12 13.14.15.16.17.</note> and becauſe thou wilt be ſure to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, ſpeake euill of them that are in authority, reſiſt the ordinance of God, and ſo ſuffer for euill doing? If thou be one of the Lords iuſtified faithfull ones, thou ſhalt finde aduerſaries enow euery day, though law and authority ſhould bee on thy ſide, and take thy part.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hee is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God for thy wealth.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid,</hi> though he were King himſelfe, and none in the world aboue him but God, yet could hee not preuent the mockes and taunts, and drunken ſongs that were of him, nor yet the manifold enemies that purſued his ſoule night and day, wherefore he cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied himſelfe, and prayed oft with a broken heart and a contrite ſpirit, to him that was able to deliuer him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thoſe his ghoſtly enemies, watering his cheeks and bed full many a time and oft with teares: Learne therefore to take vp <hi>Dauids</hi> Croſſe, to ſuffer and to be crucified with him, &amp; with Chriſt his Lord, learne to be Chriſts Diſciple and ſeruants as <hi>Dauid</hi> was, and to loue the Lord, and walke in his waies as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, and thou ſhalt haue enemies enow wil find thee out,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19603:53"/>both naturall and ſpirituall, thou ſhalt not neede to goe ſeeke them, onely take vp thy Croſſe willingly and with patience: and then if thou ſo ſuffer with him, thou ſhalt be ſure alſo to raigne with him.</p>
            <p>Shew me one word in all the new Teſtament, that requireth thee to ſuffer for thoſe thinges that thou pretendeſt, or tell mee which of the Apoſtles, or Chriſtians, in the Apoſtles times did ſuffer for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt, or diſobeying the law of ceremonies, except it were vniuſtly:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 25.7.8.</note> and then <hi>Paul</hi> (when the Iewes laide many and greeuous complaints againſt him which they could not proue) anſweres for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, That he had neither offended any thing againſt the law of the Iewes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.14, 15.</note> nor againſt the Temple, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> onely he ſought Chriſt Ieſus, in whom all thoſe things which the Iewes called hereſie, were accompliſht, and the vſe of them no more of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,but were then become all indifferent.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>18.19.20.</label> I ſay, ſhew mee one that euer did ſuffer for thoſe, or the like things, that you our Reformiſts or Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts, or Anabaptiſts doe now pretende: That God by his Goſpell and new Teſtament, doth approue, and we will then acknowledge, ye haue the truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, and doe ſuffer for righteouſneſſe: Or elſe, know this, that you are they the Scripture ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of: Makers of Sects, fleſhly hauing not the ſpirit, and deſpiſe gouernement, ſpeaking euill of them that are in authority,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8.</note> ſeparating your ſelues from others, being puft vp, knowing nothing, doting about que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and ſtrife of wordes, whereof commeth enuy, raylings, ſtrife, and euill ſurmiſings.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:19603:53"/>
            <p> And are not thoſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.21.</note> that edifie themſelues in the moſt holy faith, praying in the holy Ghoſt, and that keepe themſelues in the loue of God, looking for the mercies of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt vnto eternall life.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11.12. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17.</note> And if ye ſuffer for theſe things, bleſſed are ye.</p>
            <p>Neither thinke that if thou giueſt ouer thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, about theſe differences (of thine) and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with ſhaddows, that then thou muſt needs take thy pleaſure in this world, and ſhake handes with it, and looke after preferments in the earth, and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as others ſome doe: Neither take me, as if I iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie thoſe that haue turned their heat into coldnes; nor yet thoſe that can play with both hands, becauſe they will keepe their credite with thoſe that are zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and not loſe that neither which they gape for whenſoeuer it fals, who are fedde till they are groſſe with fat, and yet gape for more: Theſe are the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninger ſort of ſubſcribing Reformers, who ſpeake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of that in priuate, which they conform to in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, who vnder pretence of preaching the Goſpell for the good of others, preach and preferments, who reigne in their ſpirits and word, more like Lords then many of thoſe whoſe places, and titles, and honours, they ſpight and ſpeake againſt, becauſe it is not theirs. Neither do I iuſtifie any that hauing authority (more or leſſe) doe raigne as Lordes ouer Gods heritage, that loue ſalutations and greetings, delighting to be called Lords, affecting greatly the Title Rabby, ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues with the afflictions of <hi>Iacob,</hi> that tread the holy Citie Ieruſalem vnder their feete, as
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19603:54"/>the Popes and Lords of Rome haue done, and doe.</p>
            <p>For as I condemne no one for his greatneſſe of place, or Titles, or power and authority whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: ſo no more doe I iuſtifie the euill workes of any, but know and am aſſured, that whoſoeuer he be that doth loue the wages of <hi>Balam,</hi> and doth poſt after <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lakes</hi> preferment, as <hi>Balam</hi> did, is no better then hee. And alſo whoſoeuer doth the workes of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees and Scribes, and of their generation (the ſonnes of the whore of Babylon) ſhall be found (as indeede they are) the very of-ſpring of thoſe Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees: and the children of that whore, their moher, though they diſclaime her neuer ſo much: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thogh they come like ſheep, prophecying in the name of Chriſt, preaching oftentimes his word and truth, as <hi>Balam</hi> did; and like thoſe whom our Sauior ſpeaketh of, yet we muſt beware of them, as of falſe Prophets: And we ſhall know them hardly by their cloathing, which is their preaching and doctrines, for therein they can and doe oftentimes imitate the Sheepe, But by their fruits (ſaith the Lord) yee ſhall know them.</p>
            <p>And therefore (eſpecially) this I iuſtifie, wiſh and deſire, that all (that profeſſe Chriſt and his Goſpell and the adminiſtration thereof) would take heede, they reſiſt not the power, ſeeing it is the Ordinance of God, and that they would not bee high minded, but feare.</p>
            <p>And alſo that they, that haue authority and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and haue a great place, as they profeſſe Chriſt and his Diuine word, and the miniſtration thereof: that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19603:54"/>they would doe the workes of Chriſt in meekeneſſe and lowlines of heart, louing the righteous, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the little ones, knowing that he that is the greateſt ſhall be as the leaſt, and he that is cheefe, as him that ſerueth, then ſhall they bee worthy of dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble honour.</p>
            <p>Now let vs ſpeake a little of ſome of the greateſt things that God requireth at our handes: the which we haue greateſt neede to looke after, to practiſe and performe: and that is, to bee borne againe of water and the holy Ghoſt: I hat is to ſay, the true teares of repentance, and the fire of Gods loue, by the power of the holy Ghoſt: without the which, we ſhall neuer enter into the Kingdome of heauen. And though we ſhould giue to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the thinges that bee <hi>Caeſars,</hi> yet are we neuer the neerer to the Kingdome of heauen, except we giue vnto God the things that are Gods.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt effect of the ſpirit in vs, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that God is, and is to be found. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. The ſecond effect of the ſpirit, for which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and word of faith is made and giuen, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</note>Firſt therefore whoſoeuer commeth to God, muſt beleeue that God is, and that he is alſo a rewarder of them that ſeeke him: for no man commeth vnto God to be borne againe, and reconciled vnto him, but he muſt firſt beleeue that he is, euer was, and ſhall be, and is onely able to ſaue, and willing (alſo) and ready to be found of them that ſeeke him: Now then the firſt worke which the Lord doth worke in vs ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall to ſaluation, is repentance, and is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our regeneration, and the firſt ſteppe of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God after wee beleeue that hee is, and is to bee found. And this repentance is an vnſpeakeable ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſinnes, &amp; deſire of reconciliation with God, with ſuch a moulten and diſſolued heart, as yeeldeth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19603:55"/>forth thouſands of teares, from the deepe digged well of water, broken vp from the bottome of that his ſorrowfull heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.4.</note> waſhing, and baptiſing it therin, bewailing his wofull and loſt condition in his father <hi>Adam;</hi> and the loathſome vncleanneſſe of his owne life, which the righteous law of God had moſt iuſtly condemned him for, Sighing, and ſobbing, beeing borne and become, euen as water, crying, and calling for mercy night and day:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5.</note> neuer giuing ouer, till God takes pitty vppon him, and ſend downe the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto his oppreſſed ſoule,<note place="margin">The third ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is peace &amp; loue The aſſurance of Gods fauor &amp; forgiuenes of our ſinnes.</note> with the fire of his loue, to kindle peace therein, and to purge the ſame: according to his promiſe, made in the ſlaine Lambe the onely mediator betweene God and all ſuch heauy loaded ſinners, prepared, digged, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red full of water, like <hi>Elias</hi> his Sacrifice: which fire of heauen, doth ſo conſume, and licke vp, this wette and well prepared Sacrifice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> that the odor thereof is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp by the comforter, (the holy Ghoſt) the Angell which the Lambe did ſend vnto him, who doth carry and recarry, from heauen to earth, and from earth to heauen: who (with golden cenſure) doth receiue and preſent with much odors that is giuen him, the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 8.34.5.</note> cryes, and teares, of this poore ſighing ſoule: offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them vpon the golden Altar, which is before the throane of God: where the fire of his loue dooth burne night and day: and the ſmoake of the odors, with their requeſts, the cries, and teares, of this dry &amp; thirſty ſoule, Aſcend vp before God out of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels hand: who maketh interceſſion for him, in the mediation of the Lambe, Requeſting grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19603:55"/>for him, for the mediators ſake, and that hee would regard and pitty his ſoule, whoſe meſſengers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> theſe cryes and teares are, ſtanding before the face of God, among his Angels to beſeene, which grace and loue, God doth grant vnto his Angell for him: who with ſpeed taketh the Cenſer and filleth it with the fire of the Altar, and haſteth downe to power it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this and all ſuch like poore thirſty ſoules. The ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt meſſenger that any man can haue: bringing peace and comfort, loue and ioy: Aſſuring him it is decreed in heauen, that he ſhall liue. And this is to be borne of water, and of the holy Ghoſt, and this is it which <hi>Iohn</hi> meaneth when he ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11.12.</note> I baptiſe you with water to repentance, but he that commeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me, ſhal baptiſe you with the holy Ghoſt and fire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17.</note> The ſacrifice of God (ſaith one) is a broken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 42.3.</note> A broken and contrite heart (oh God) thou wilt not diſpiſe. Thou wilt binde vp the bruſed reed: and giue fire to the ſmoaking Flax.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.6.</note> This is the generation of them ſeeke him, yea of them that ſeeke thy face oh God, euen <hi>Iacob</hi> my beloued.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.8.</note> Seeke yee my face, my heart anſwered: O Lord I will ſeeke thy face. The ſecrets of the Lord are opened to them that feare him and his couenant, to giue them vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10.</note> This is the man that can not onely giue <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that; are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> But to God (alſo) the things that are Gods, he offereth eueryday, the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a broken heart, ſighing, and weeping to ſee his ſinnes looke on him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.35.</note> which hee hath caſt behinde him, mourning to ſee how his fleſh doth ſerue ſinne, whereas his minde doth loue, and delight in the lawe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19603:56"/>of God his louing father: who hath his heart (night and day) attending on his grace: thinking on his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſtill; neuer putting out of minde, what hee hath done for him; alwaies thinking, where euer hee goes, of his moſt pretious promiſes, wondring at his great loue. Vttering moſt ioyfull voices by himſelfe alone: vnexpreſſable ioyes in the holy Ghoſt hath hee often times, and peace paſt vnderſtanding, thus doth hee walke with God and pleaſe him. The night watches doth hee preuent, and the Sun riſing to giue thanks vnto his God, and doth ſalute him, before the day ſpring. Thus doth God poſſeſſe him, and he him.</p>
            <p>Are not theſe thinges true Maſter <hi>Smith?</hi> (well, time wil tell) peraduenture you will obiect, that I ſay but prooue nothing: If heere bee nothing prooued, you may the more eaſily diſprooue: for no man will gaine-ſay that which he taketh prooued, if he be not poſſeſt with an euill ſpirit. But it may bee you thinke ſcorne to fight with one that hath no weapon, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it no praiſe, nor tryumph in ſuch a victory: well, though you will neither fight nor yield, (as one that diſdaineth ſo meane an offer) yet truth ſhall winne, though ye diſpiſe to learne of her, and ſcorne to ſpeak vnto her: But if you doe, yet bethinke your ſelfe, leaſt you ſhold be thought to be put to ſilence by a foole, and take heed (I pray you) kick not againſt the pricks, let not the wiſedome of the fleſh ouer-rule you: It is better, a wiſe man ſhould yeild a little to a foole, then that the wiſe man ſhould die at the point of truth: for it is ſharper then any two edged ſword. Take heede therefore, and marke well the thinges that are heere
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19603:56"/>written vnto you, and ſearch the Scriptures, whether they be ſo or no: for they are GODS witneſſes, and they tell the truth, what euer man ſaies: and I pray you take heede, you miſtake not the Lord: for his word is a miſtery, eſpecially theſe things, which are called the ſecrets of the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>And beware that you affirme not any thing, which he hath not ſaid nor meant: nor gain-ſay, or diminiſh any thing from his intent, and howſoeuer ye haue failed therein already: yet conſidering (as I perſwade my ſelfe) you are not of thoſe, louers and makers of lies, for I hope farre better things of you M. <hi>Smith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 22.15.</note> and therefore that we may vnderſtand the Lord, and ſee his ſecrets, euen the ſecrets of his kingdome: Let vs intreate him with broken and humble hearts, for the ſpirit of trueth, that holy annointing, which is true, and not lying: that as it doth teach vs, euen ſo we may abide in him, and ſo let vs write and ſpeake. Let vs annoint our eyes with eye ſalue, that we may ſee, euen with the water of a diſſolued broken heart, and we ſhall ſee better things, then forme and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That we may diſcerne, betweene thoſe that haue but the forme of godlineſſe, and them that haue the power thereof. That wee may ſee and know thoſe little ones: whom to receiue, is to receiue the Lord: and to loue them, whom to loue, is to loue the Lord, and to loue the Lord, is life for euermore. And this is that loue, without the which, all knowledge, and all faith, doth but make vs as ſounding braſſe, and tinckling Cimballs. For by this loue,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3.</note> we ſhall know that we are tranſlated from death to life, and by this
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19603:57"/>loue, we ſhal approue our ſelues to the little ones, to haue that one peculiar faith with them, the aſſurance of the loue of God vnto vs in Chriſt Ieſus, and of our reconciliation with God through him.</p>
            <p>And this is the faith which one ſpeaketh of (in a certaine place) to one that would haue beene eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.18.19.20.</note> and no doubt eſteeming of himſelfe too, as if he had that ſpeciall peculiar faith, which only the Lords redeemed haue. Shew me (ſaith he) thy faith by thy works, and I will ſhew thee my faith by my workes: Thou haſt faith I graunt thee, and doſt beleeue, but what? that there is one God (well) yea and one Lord Ieſus Chriſt alſo, and one holy ſpirit, and one faith, and one baptiſme, yea and one Church, purchaſed and ſanctified by the bloud of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. And doſt thou beleeue all theſe things indeed? thou doſt well: but I tell thee, the diuell doth beleeue it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and doth tremble: for one may haue faith, though not that ſpeciall faith, nor yet the fruites that follow the ſame. One may by faith caſt out diuels, and that in the name of Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22.23.</note> and do many great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and yet a worker of iniquity.</p>
            <p>What then, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> doth not man liue by his faith alone, doth works make his faith aliue?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> Man doth liue by his faith alone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Haba.</hi> 2.4.</note> yea the iuſt man, and his faith doth make his works aliue, as the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of a Tree receiue their ſappe and life from the roote.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> what faith is this you meane, are there many kindes of faith? and the Scripture ſaith, one faith, one baptiſme, and ſo.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:19603:57"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> The Scriptures meane, one faith to life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.15.</note> and one baptiſme to life (as it ſaith) Whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhall not be confounded, and that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhall not periſh, but haue eternall life: And againe, whoſoeuer beleeueth and is bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16.</note> ſhall be ſaued. What then (will you ſay) is there a faith and baptiſme which men may haue, &amp; periſh? Yea: for <hi>Iudas</hi> beleeued, and was baptiſed:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>Simon Magus</hi> beleeued, and was baptiſed: and many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more, which yet ſhall be found the workers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> You will ſay then, what faith is that, that you meane, may it be diſtinguiſht from the other?</p>
            <p>It may: But firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> I will tell you what I take the word faith to meane, as it is wrought in men in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, reſpecting God: It is an vndoubted perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wrought in the heart, by the force and power of the holy Ghoſt, in the reuelation of the worde of God, of the truth of all, or ſome, or any of the things thereby reuealed: for faith is the ground of thinges hoped for,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</note> and alſo the euidence of the thinges not ſeene. By faith men vnderſtand that there is onely one God, &amp; that the world was created by his word. By faith men beleeue, that whatſoeuer hath beene ſaid, or done in the world, by God, his ſeruants, his Prophets and Apoſtles, are all true, and were done by the power of God: yea by faith men haue and doe worke wonders themſelues. As all theſe things may be vnderſtoode, and done by faith, and yet ſuch beleeuers and workers (for all their faithfulneſſe) may goe to hell.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:19603:58"/>
            <p> So there is a myſterie reuealed, that whoſoeuer doth beleeue, ſhall not periſh, but ſhall haue eternall life:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.1.2.3.</note> that is to ſay, a word of great grace and mercy giuen out, a couenant of life and peace, of pardon and deliuerance, made to the poore, and broken in heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.5.28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.24.</note> the weary and heauie loaden, the loſt ſheepe, the hungry and thirſty, the contrite and broken ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, euen to him that doth repent. And none can beleeue this word and promiſe of life and pardon, aſſuredly to pertain vnto themſelues, but theſe alone. And of this ſeeker alone is God found, to him doth he looke for his ſonnes ſake, the Mediator of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.3.</note> and doth write him bleſſed, and doth aſſure him pardon and reconciliation by his promiſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: whereby he is ſealed, and hath ſet to his ſeale, that God is true: and is fully aſſured, that God is true: and is fully aſſured, that God loueth him in Chriſt Ieſus, and that his name is written in the booke of life. And this is faith alſo which doth beleeue this thing, and this is the thing, that doth diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene it and the other: and this faith if you wil that I ſhall define in few wordes: It is a full and certaine perſwaſion, wrought in the poore and broken heart, by the comforter, of peace and reconciliation with God, in and through Chriſt Ieſus his Lord: and this is the faith which worketh by loue, and this is that peculiar faith ſpoken of before, and is but one, &amp; was euer the ſame.</p>
            <p>Nowe concerning that one Baptiſme a little more. As in the olde time, there was Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the skinne, and Circumciſion of the heart,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19603:58"/>but the Circumciſion of the heart was the onely chiefe Circumciſion, which whoſoeuer had, was onely a true Iſraelite: So likewiſe, in this new time, there is the Baptiſme of the skinne, and the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of the heart: but the Baptiſme of the heart, is the onely chiefe baptiſme,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</note> and they that are ſo bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, are the onely true Chriſtians and Iſrael of God, and is but one and the ſame for euer: In compariſon whereof, that which is but outward on the skinne, is none at all.</p>
            <p>And tell mee Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> are not theſe thinges true indeede, dare you to reſiſt and gain-ſay them, do you not know that which is of God ſhall ſtand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.38.39.</note> and that which is of men, ſhall fall and come to nought? Take heede therefore, leaſt ye be found a fighter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. But you may ſay to me, thou art a ſinfull wretch, and if I write againſt thee, I write but againſt a wretched one. It is true indeede, and therefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy I am to write or ſpeake of theſe holy things: And as for me, ſpare me not for my ſinnes, but yet let the truth goe free: for the Lords ſake whoſe it is, and for his childrens ſake to whom it may come, and for your owne ſake leaſt you die.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> But ſome will ſay (perhaps) Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> is too wiſe (I trow) to fight with, or to yeelde to ſuch a foole, that hath not one <hi>maior</hi> or <hi>minor,</hi> but all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimes, too too little for his great capacity. Alacke, Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> regards it not, he ſcarſe looked on it, it is ſo meane, he will not file his hands, to anſwer ſuch a clowniſh diſcourſe, that hath not one artificiall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in it, and ſo void of learning, that it hath not
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19603:59"/>ſo much as method, but plaine like the plough. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacke, Maſter <hi>Smiths</hi> bringing vp hath not beene ſo Swineheard and Shepheard like: He is a Scholler of no ſmall reading, and well ſeene and experienced in Arts. If hee thought his anſwere to Maſter <hi>Clifton,</hi> would be the leſſe eſteemed, for that hee is helde a weake man (but that his allegations and reaſons are the beſt plea of the greateſt Rabbies themſelues) Thinke not that he will weaken his cauſe to anſwere thee. If it were any of the Rabbies of England, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other harlot whatſoeuer, you ſhould ſee then what he would ſay to it: for although Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> doe publiſh anſweres to Maſter <hi>Clifton,</hi> one of the ſeparation (on Maſter <hi>Iohnſons</hi> ſide) chalenging them eſpecially to the combat, yet he proclaimeth, ſaying, Be it knowne to all the ſeparation, that wee account them, in reſpect of their conſtitution, to be as very an harlot, as either her mother England, or her grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother Rome, out of whoſe loines ſhe came.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> As her Mother England! whoſe ſonne is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Smith,</hi> if one might aske, where was hee borne, and where had he his education, and bringing vp, In England? yea in England. Is this a kind ſonne to vſe his mother thus: not onely to runne away from her, like his followe brethren, againſt whom alſo he doth proteſt; but to raile againſt her ſo. Is this your Logick ſir, was this your bringing vp, hath Art cauſed you ſo much to forget Nature. If not grace yet mee thinkes the light of nature ſhould haue taught you better: If you had beene borne in America, or in Rome it ſelfe: very nature might haue perſwaded you, that ſome
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19603:59"/>might bee there, that had rather die, then wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip diuels, or bowe to <hi>Baal,</hi> Much more in England, though you be runne out for feare: tell mee whether can any man runne, in all the world, to mend himſelfe at this day? And although your mother England, hath too many diſobedient and froward children, yet if you had beene a Naturall ſonne, you would haue ſtayed at home, and if you had receiued a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light then the reſt of your brethren: Loue would haue forced you to haue laide downe your life for them, rather then they ſhould haue beene vntaught therein: (conſidering alſo what great hope is to bee conceiued of England, aboue any one Nation in the world,) and not to leaue them in the darke, and cry out, a harlot, a harlot, no Church viſible, nor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to be ſeene: no faith, but the faith of diuels: no Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but the marke of the beaſte, no Church to bee ſeene in the world, but I <hi>Iohn Smith</hi> and my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
            <p>Is this your ſhameleſſe voice? Dare you be ſo bold to ſet vp a flag of defiance againſt the City of God? Be it knowne vnto you, that the leaſt Citizen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is able to meete both you and all your company in the field, and through the ſtrength of the Lord thereof, (without either bow or ſhield) euen by the word of his mouth, put you all to flight. And for all your great bragges, and flagges: Bee it knowne vnto you, and vnto all the world this day; That his holy Citie is in England, euen Ieruſalem that is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and although ſhe hath many, yea and too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny entercommoners, yet ſhe hath free Deniſons,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19603:60"/>who pertake of her priuiledges, whoſe feete walke in our ſtreetes, though the world regard it not: and if ye will not beleeue me, wipe but your eyes with Sacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and come and ſee, and if you will doe neither, anſwere in the field, and although heere bee neither Art, nor learning, and therefore you know not how to frame your pen to ſtoope ſo low: Remember where once you were, from whence you came, know that reaſon brought forth Art, and therefore was before: Let Art then, beeing the daughter (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhee be ſo high) looke downe a little to her mother, and let both, and all, and euery creature bend and yeeld vnto the word of the Lord, which ſhall endure for euer.</p>
            <p>And although it be none of the Rabbies, but one of the vnlearned babies, yet meete him, ſeeing hee doth accept the challenge, but looke well to your forehead, for all your Artificiall Armes and skill to vſe them, for little <hi>Dauid</hi> beeing a keeper of ſheepe, though he knew not how to ſtir himſelfe in ſuch like armor, yet comming in the name of the God of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, from the ſheepe, with his ſling and a ſtone, ſtroake <hi>Goliah</hi> ſo deadly, that hee fell downe, and with his owne ſword, cut of his head: wherefore looke vnto it, it is dangerous ſtriuing with trueth, for although Kings be ſtrong, and Wine is ſtrong, and Women are ſtronger then either of both, who beare Kings and the planters of Vines, and all Maſters of Artes, and ſciences whatſoeuer: yet truth is ſtronger then all, and all muſt bend, and bow and yeeld to her, leaſt they die at the point thereof. And though it come
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19603:60"/>out of the mouth of very babes and ſucklings, yet it is ſtronger then <hi>Goliah</hi> withall his forces. Not that I deſpiſe learning, but reuerence it, and doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my ſelfe to be vnworthy thereof: but only this, It muſt not be ſo proud, to thinke that trueth ſhould learne of it: or to thinke that reaſon muſt not rule it, and if Art ſhould thinke (for it is like Nature, very blind) that truth and reaſon could ouerſhoot it ſelfe, yet were it the part of an humble daughter, to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere her mother, with mildnes and not diſdaine.</p>
            <p>And now Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> where you triumph and praiſe God, you ſay in the end of your anſwer, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht againſt the obiections of one Maſter <hi>Clifton,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring your ſelfe of the trueth of your opinions: ſo that neither he, nor all the earth, ſhall euer be able to wring them out of your heart and hands.</p>
            <p>So, and more then ſo, I praiſe the Lord my God, for that he hath aſſiſted me againſt you and your lies: and I haue receiued ſo much more aſſurance of the trueth of that which I haue written vnto you, then you haue of that which you haue ſaid, as there is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene a truth and a lie. And I boldly (in the name of my Lord, and for his choſen ſake) cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge not all the earth, but you, and all, or any one of your company, to anſwere directly and without col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loring or painting, to that which hath beene ſaid, or elſe to ſubſcribe vnto it according to your promiſe.</p>
            <p>Though theſe things be not ratified by you, nor written in your bookes, yet behold, they are true, and although they be but few, and goe but ſimple, yet they ſhall ſtand and be had in honour, when much
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19603:61"/>and many things ſhall faile: not that I preſume vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſtrength of mine owne arme, for it is like a broken bow, but my ſtrength is the Lord, and in him I will reioyce, and that hee hath written my name in his booke of life: for which grace, and all other his mercies, his name be praiſed for euer. AMEN.</p>
            <p>And thus Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> I thought Good to write vnto you, and to the company with you, of whom I haue great hope, God wil deliuer them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the errors and diſtractions of theſe times, and that others falles will driue you to looke better about you: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I haue beene ſomewhat bould with you, yet I pray you take it not in the euill part; for truly, God is my record, that for his truthes ſake, and for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens ſakes, and for your ſakes haue I written, that you, and we, and all might perceiue the trueth, and walke therein, and for no other reſpect: and howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer theſe things may ſeeme ſtrange vnto you, yet if you conſider them well, you ſhall finde them not ſo ſtrange as true. And although thoſe little ones, be now more rare, and more ſeldome ſeene then the truth, in the fielde, yet that which hath beene ſaide of them is true.</p>
            <p>And let vs not labour any longer, to cut and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the truth, like our ſelues, but let vs ſtudie and ſtriue to become our ſelues, both in vnderſtanding and in doing, like the truth: Let vs not deceiue our ſelues with ſhadowes, for they fly away, but let vs take hold of the ſu bſtance and roote it ſelfe, which is able to defend vs in the ſtormy day: let vs ſtoope, and put on the yoake of the Lord, for he was meeke and of a
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19603:61"/>lowly heart, his dwelling was among the little ones, and the leaſt was the greateſt with him, yea he taſted his teares with them, and wept alſo for thoſe whoſe hearts could not affoord a teare for themſelues; hee ſought out that which was loſt, and the broken did he binde vp: This was our Lord, let vs learne of him; and theſe were his companions, and on earth his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friends.</p>
            <p>But now alacke, where are theſe litle ones become? Doe the high looke of theſe proud times, make them aſhamed to ſhewe their caſt-downe eye? Oh come forth ye habitation of the Lord, althogh (indeed) there boldneſſe may make you bluſh, and ſhew your face, for we haue heard, that he which is with you, is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then he that is with them: And what is the cauſe they are ſo ſeldome ſeene this day? One thing is, they are few: Another thing is, they that ſought them, miſt the way that ledde to their Tents: They ſought them vpon the Mountaines, and in the drie places; but they were in the Valleyes among the water plaſhes, filling the Lords bottle with Teares: They ſought them among the great, but they were of the little ones: They ſought them among the learned, and men of great ſtudy and long experience, but they were ſitting among the little children, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping with the tender babes. And thus they ſought but found not: How hard a thing it is to ſuppreſſe thoſe harts of ours: Ah let vs teare them in peeces, and intreat the Lord with thouſand of teares, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the drowſie fatnes that droppeth vpon them, that we may find the way to the dwellings of his lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones, where alſo his owne habitation is, and ſee
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19603:62"/>and enter into his Kingdome of heauen, where alſo we may behold theſe his brethren, and loue them, and be knowne, and loued of them; whereby we ſhal all know, that our names are written in the booke of life. Theſe things let vs ſtriue for, it is time now we ſhould be eſtabliſhed in the truth, and not be carried about ſtill with euery winde.</p>
            <p>Let vs build vpon the Rocke, and then though the floods come, and the winde blow, our building ſhall ſtand: we haue pretended Diſcipline and Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a great while; but where is he that is corrected? Where is the man that hath crucified the world to himſelfe, and himſelfe to the world, and hath mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the fleſh with the workes thereof? Phariſees and Hypocrites can make cleane the out-ſide, but let vs make cleane that which is within: Wolues often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times goe in Sheepes skinnes, but Sheepe neuer in Wolues skinnes.</p>
            <p>There is a Controuerſie this day in the world where Chriſt ſhould be, whereof he hath alſo fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told vs, ſaying: Many ſhal come in my name, and ſay, here is Chriſt and there, but beleeue them not.</p>
            <p>One ſaith, I am the firſt, and I haue beene of olde, I haue kept the ſaith, and haue not erred to this day.</p>
            <p>Another ſaith, Nay thou lieſt, thou haſt loſt the faith, and haſt erred from the right way, and art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Cage of vncleane Birds this day: but I haue recouered that which thou haſt loſt, and I haue the right vſe of the Word and Sacraments, which thou haſt polluted: therefore he is here.</p>
            <p>The third comes and ſaies, Ye are both liers and Harlots, and thou that ſpake laſt, for thou art not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19603:62"/>by his lawes: he is a King, aſwell as a Prieſt and a Prophet, and therefore thou lieſt alſo: but he is here with vs, we haue his Ordinances and lawes, and are ruled by them, we haue alſo the word and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in their right kind, and ſo he is to vs a King, a Prieſt, and a Prophet.</p>
            <p>The next ſtands vp, ſaying, Who is this that boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thus, and reteyneth the baptiſme of the Whore? Muſt they not needes bee her children, ſeeing they hold her baptiſme ſufficient, and refuſe to be baptiſed aright? What? Can their baptiſme bee good, and their Church and Gouernment nought? Not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: wherefore ye are alſo deceiued, and he cannot be in the middeſt of you as you ſuppoſe.</p>
            <p>But hee is where Antichriſt with all his traſh is quite abandoned, where all is reformed, both life and doctrine: And that is here with vs, for we haue caſt off all, and haue beganne a new; we baptiſe none but men of yeares, and that doe make confeſſion of our faith, and are of vpright life: wee haue ſtrooke the right Couenant with him, therefore he is here.</p>
            <p>Then ſteppes vp the fift, with a high ſpirit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouling al, epecially the three laſt, accuſing them for wranglers, and blaſphemers, (ſaying) ye are all lyers, you are iangling contentious ſpirits, ye ſeeke Chriſt without you, ſeeke him within you, you good think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe-ones, you doe not ſo much as know what Chriſt is, nor yet what Antichriſt is: you condemne that holy auncient father, the Pope of Rome to bee the Antichriſt: the beaſt and man of ſinne, and all the holy orders of their Archprieſts, Prieſts, and offices, of good intentions; hauing all names of good ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19603:63"/>and all Images, Sacrifices, and Ceremonies, of good information: to bee all blaſphemus, Idolatrous and ſuperſtitious: and ſo blaſpheme the holy thinges, vſed in the Catholicke Church of Rome. Not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that as God did teach the world, by the orders, Sacrifices and Ceremonies, vſed among the Iewes, tell Chriſt came in the man Ieſus: So it pleaſed him alſo, to teach the world, by thoſe Orders, Images, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and Ceremonies, vſed in the Catholique Church of Rome, vntill the Chriſt came againe, now in the end of the world, according to his promiſes in his obedient man, <hi>H. N.</hi> by whom hee hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, to iudge the world, according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Not with fire and brimſtone, vpon mens heads, as we ſuppoſe, but with wiſe ſentences, with darke, and parabolous ſaying, deliuering high things, with a high ſpirit: teaching, reproouing, and condemning, the whole word, being the eight, and the laſt brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the light. The Archangel and the laſt Trumpe, none in this third and laſt day wherein Chriſt is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted. And is that Angell flying in the middeſt of heauen, hauing an euerlaſting Goſpell, to preach to them that dwell vpon the earth: Saying Chriſt is not, nor was not a man as yee ſuppoſe, but holineſſe is Chriſt: And he that doth beleeue it, is poſſible to keep all the ten commandements, hath the right faith in Chriſt, and they that doe attaine to the perfect kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of them, are riſen from the dead, according to the Scriptures, and as holines is Chriſt and the ſonne of God: So ſinne is Antichriſt and the ſonne of the diuell fight therefore againſt the Antichriſt in your ſelues, ouer come the beaſt which is the ſinne, and put on holines which is the Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:19603:63"/>
            <p> Put away therefore all your good thinkings, and all your Scripture learnedneſe, and come hether na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, for here is cloathing enough for you, for I tell your, whoſoeuer comes to learne at his ſchoole muſt be as ſimple and hold himſelfe as ignorant as a little child: for the tree of knowledge, is the tree of death, wherefore if ye will liue, come hether, did not the diuell tell you: you ſhould be as gods, and will yee beleeue him ſtill: did he deceiue you once and will you not beware: wherefore become fooles that yee may be wiſe. And here, take this booke: but keepe it cloſe, for <hi>H. N.</hi> hath many enemies, eſpecially among this wrangling crue. And therein thou ſhalt finde, an interlude, which if thou marke well, ſhall teach thee all: and harken no loner to thoſe diſturbing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: who feed thee with nothing but the forbidden fruite. Learne to liue againe in innocency, wherein thou ſhalt not not be aſhamed, though thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt goe naked, as thou didſt before? and thou ſhalt know nothing but loue, which ſhall neuer fade away and when thou haſt attained to this, thou ſhalt be in Paradice againe: and then take of the tree of life, and eate, and liue for euer.</p>
            <p>And tel me now, Is no here Chriſt indeed, and the very true Chriſt, and haue I not alſo tolde thee what is the Antichriſt, and many other worthy thinges: wherefore ſtay heere, and thou ſhalt ſee wonders in the end.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſtrange and wofull times. Are not theſe the dayes which the Lord fore-told: here is Wolfes in ſheepes cloathing on euery ſide, and yet heere are not all, but let others tell the reſt, for my part, I am
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19603:64"/>weary telling of theſe. But which way is it poſſible for the little ſheepe to eſcape theſe Wolues? euen through a very narrow way, and a ſtraight gate, which their Lord hath appointed, and made eaſie for them, for they muſt eſcape: It is not poſſible the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſhould be deceiued, the know them by their fruites.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the contentions of our dayes, who ſhall end the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie? This we are ſure of, he that hath the bride, is the bridegroome, and ſhee which hath the bridegroome, is the bride, whereſoeuer ſhee be. She hath begun to ſhew her face already, a little, and her voice hath beene heard euen in our land: but the Wolues came ſo thick about her, that ſhee was glad to retire a little into the wilderneſſe againe, but when her appointed time, and yeare, is once come, ſhe ſhal come forth, and end this controuerſie, whereby her little ones are ſo much diſmayed: in the meane time, let her poore little children reioyce and be glad, for her light ſhall ſhine euery day, ſtill more and more: and as light comes in, darkneſſe ſhall goe out, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer things ſeeme to goe.</p>
            <p>The night is euen paſſed, the day begins to break, it is but a little while &amp; the Sunne will ſhine: for the morning and euening ſacrifice muſt bee reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as in the former time, and in the dayes of old. And yet a little while, and the King of Babell, and his City both, with all his army, ſhall be ouerthrowne. And the ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhall be ſung againe; for the great City, Rome, ſhall be burnt with fire, and like the great mill-ſtone, which the Angell caſt into the See, be throwne downe, and ſhall be found no more.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19603:64"/>Then ſhall Iſraell ſing in daunces as before, ſaying, Haleluiah: Saluation, and glory, and power, be to our God, for hee hath triumphed gloriouſly. The horſe with his ſtately Rider is ouerthrowne, and his pompe turned to the graue. And then a very little while, and that day ſo long looked for, ſhall ſhew it ſelfe, wherein that poore diſtreſſed, and deſolate wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, toſſed with tempeſt too &amp; fro, who hath ſo long attended, with many a wet eye, and watchfull looke, and her lamp alwaies ready burning, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of her husband to the wedding day: wherein he wil giue her a crowne of life, and wipe her eyes for euer weeping more: and giue her ioy and gladneſſe, in ſteed of mourning: and beauty, and euerlaſting life, and glory, in ſtead of duſt and deſolation.</p>
            <p>Great and meruailous are thy workes, Lord God Almighty, true and righteous are thy iudgements, King of Saints, who ſhall not feare thee, oh Lord, &amp; giue glory to thy name, for thy iudgements are made manifeſt. Let vs be glad and reioyce, and giue glory to him, for the mariage of the Lamb is come, &amp; his wife hath made her ſelfe ready.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſai. 14. 4. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>How hath the oppreſſor ceaſed, and the gold-thirſtie Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell reſted! Since thou waſt laid low, no hewer came vp againſt vs.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:65"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>ANd if any man thinke heere is not ſo much ſaid againſt them, as their faults deſerue: Let him conſider, if one ſhould lay open to others all his faults at once, with their due deſerts, he would take it very vnkindly, and very hardly euer receiue an admonition (at his hands) in good part that ſhould ſo ſerue him. Therefore to preuent this euill, I haue rather laboured to tell them what they ſhould be, then to lay open what they are, for loue hopeth the beſt, till it ſee the worſt. And this I aſſure both thee &amp; them, that no man euer was more forward and ſtrict in outward obſeruations, nor more ready to contend about the forme and manner of religious exerciſes, and carnall waſhings, and all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Kingdome, then the very hippocrite, that neuer intended the purging of his heart, nor yet to partake in her peculiar things, though vnder the cloake of the one, he doth pretend the greateſt part in the other. Make cleane then the inſide firſt, and the out-ſide ſhall bee cleane; for whoſoeuer is cleanſed in heart, neede not bee taught to waſh his hands.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19603:65"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
